How's life?
生活怎么样？
I mean, yeah, all the Wu-Tang Clan pretty young.
我的意思是，是的，所有的 Wu-Tang Clan 都很年轻，
that was kind of [], Wu-Tang.
这是一种[]， Wu-Tang 。
There's no Wu-Tang questions on the exam this year,
今年的考试没有 Wu-Tang 的问题，
previous year have been,
之前的年份有，
so don't feel like you need to know these things.
所以不要感觉你需要知道这些事情。
All right, again awesome, 2PL.
好的，太棒了， 2PL 。
You guys, lot to go over,
你们有很多事要做，
the list is getting longer.
列表越来越长。
So project #1 is due this Sunday at midnight,
所以项目 #1 在本周日午夜截止，
again, we're having special office hours on, on Saturday, that's in person,
再次，我们周六有特别的办公时间，是面对面的，
they announced it on Piazza,
他们在 Piazza 上宣布了这个消息，
I think it's on the fifth floor
我想是在五楼，
and one to make [].
一个是给[]。
Homework #2, it's been bumped out to October 4th, so Wednesday,
家庭作业 #2 被推迟到了 10 月 4 日，星期三，
make sure made not have be the same due date as project #1.
确保截止日期和项目 #1 不同。
Homework #3 will be out this week,
作业 #3 将在本周发布，
that's will due four days later.
截止日期是四天以后。
And again, that kind of sucks,
再次，这很糟糕，
that it kind of cram it so quickly,
这么快就把它塞进去了，
but because the midterm exam,
但是因为期中考试，
which will cover things, will cover things that in in homework #3,
它将涵盖家庭作业 #3 的内容，
we want to get that back to you guys and graded,
我们想把它带回给你们，并评分，
before the the midterm exam on on Wednesday.
在星期三的期中考试之前。
So midterm, midterm it be in class here on October 11th,
所以期中考试将在 10 月 11 日在这里，
it's a wednesday and during the regular class time,
它是星期三，在正常的上课时间，
if you need accommodations, please email us
如果你需要住宿，请给我们发邮件，
and so we can start organizing and taking care of the logistics,
这样我们就可以开始组织和照顾后勤，
don't post on Piazza.
不要贴在 Piazza 上。
We're trying to get homework #3 out now,
我们现在正试着把作业 #3 放出来，
it should be out today,
今天应该就能出来了，
I don't know if it be out today.
我不知道今天会不会放出。
Yes, that's the plan,
是的，这就是计划，
but the trouble is like, it doesn't cover things,
但问题是，它并不包括，
it's doesn't cover sorting and Joins,
它不包括排序和 Join ，
which I'll cover next week.
我将在下周介绍。
Any questions about any of these things?
对这些东西有什么问题吗？
Yes.
是的。
Whatever it says on the website now is the current plan, yes.
现在网站上的任何内容都是当前的计划，是的。
At the end of fall break,
在秋假结束时，
we double check that,
我们会仔细检查这个，
I thought we moved it,
我以为我们把它移走了，
so we didn't have to do fall break,
这样我们就不用在秋假做了，
we will take care of that.
我们会处理好的。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
All right, cool.
好的，酷。
All right, so,
好的，那么，
the the last two classes we've talked about data structures,
最后两节课，我们讨论了数据结构，
we talked about hash tables
我们讨论了哈希表，
and then we talked about B+ trees,
然后我们讨论了 B+ 树，
and I prefaced our conversation
我之前说过，
going into discussing the hash table B+ trees stuff,
在开始讨论哈希表和 B+ 树时，
to say that to simplify the discussion
为了简化讨论，
and, and the, the explanation of these data structures and the algorithms,
以及对这些数据结构和算法的解释，
that are used to to manipulate them or work with them,
那些用于操作它们或使用它们的，
we're going to assume that it's single threaded,
我们假设它是单线程的，
because that just makes your life easier,
因为这只会让你的生活更轻松，
but of course, in any modern system,
但是当然，在任何现代系统中，
in today's hardware,
在今天的硬件中，
you need to support multiple threads or multiple workers running at the same time,
你需要支持多个线程或多个 worker 同时运行，
again, I'm going to try to use the word workers,
同样，我将尝试使用 worker 一词，
because that can mean either a thread or process,
因为它可以表示线程或进程，
Postgres is not multi thread, it's multi process,
Postgres 不是多线程，而是多进程，
most modern systems are multi threaded,
大多数现代系统都是多线程的，
but the idea is the same.
但理念是一样的。
But still again we want to be able to have multiple workers running at the same time
不过，我们还是希望能够让多个 worker 同时运行，
be able to access these data structures,
能够访问这些数据结构，
so that if one of them has to stall,
这样，如果其中一个必须停顿，
because they're going to disk,
因为它们要访问磁盘，
we can have other workers run at the same time
我们可以让其他 worker 同时运行，
and do useful things, right.
并做一些有用的事情。
System will look very unresponsive,
系统将看起来非常迟钝，
if you only have a single worker,
如果你只有一个 worker ，
again, assume it's a thread
再次，假设它是一个线程，
and then I'm going to go run some query,
然后我将运行一些查询，
and then as soon as I have to go my page table,
然后当我必须去我的页表时，
and the thing I don't need is,
我不需要的东西是，
the page I need isn't there,
我需要的页面不在那里，
I have to stall,
我必须停顿，
because I got to go to disk and get it.
因为我必须去磁盘上获取它。
While, while we're stalled,
当我们停滞不前时，
the CPU essentially stalled,
CPU 基本上也停滞不前了，
we can have other threads, other workers do useful things.
我们可以让其他线程，其他 worker 做有用的事情。
So that's the goal of of what we're going to talk about today
这就是我们今天要讨论的目标，
is how do we actually make these data structures thread safe.
就是我们如何真正使这些数据结构线程安全。
And so what I'll say is that,
所以我要说的是，
this is how most systems are going to be implemented,
这就是大多数系统将会实现的，
most systems will try to take advantage of multiple threads,
大多数系统都会尝试利用多线程，
there, there's sort of category systems,
有一种[分类]系统，
that actually don't do any of the things we're talking about today,
不会做我们今天所说的任何事情，
and the most famous one is Redis,
最著名的是 Redis ，
that it's a single process, single thread,
它是一个单进程、单线程，
so all the latching stuff we're going to talk about today,
所以我们今天要讨论的所有锁的东西，
they don't have to do,
他们都不需要做，
because they know no other threads running at the same time.
因为它们不知道没有其他线程同时运行。
There'll be other systems they have,
还会有其他系统，它们有，
they'll still be multi threaded,
它们仍然是多线程的，
but they'll maybe have only one writer thread,
但它们可能只有一个写线程，
but multiple reader threads running at the same time,
但是有多个读线程同时运行，
and that simplifies a bunch of things,
这简化了很多事情，
but you still need the latching protections that we're going to talk about today.
但你仍然需要我们今天要讨论的锁保护。
So that the, the thing that we're going to use
所以，我们将使用的东西，
to, to enforce the threads or workers to behave a certain way,
强制线程或 worker 以特定方式运行，
so that we don't end up with corrupted data and invalid data structures
这样我们最终就不会出现损坏的数据和无效的数据结构，
is going to be called a concurrent control protocol.
将被称为并发控制协议。
And again, for today's class,
再次，在今天的课上，
we're going to see how we do this for workers,
我们将看到我们如何为 worker 做这件事，
after the midterm,
期中考试结束后，
we'll discuss how we use concurrcncy control to, to coordinate transactions.
我们将讨论如何使用并发控制来协调事务。
And so you can sort of think of this,
所以你可以这样想，
this concurrency control protocol is like the traffic cop of the system,
这种并发控制协议就像系统的交通警察，
that allows you to tell, tell different workers,
允许告诉不同的 worker ，
who's allowed to do what at what given time, right.
谁被允许在给定的时间做什么。
And the idea is that,
我们的想法是，
they're going to be operating on some shared object or some critical section,
它们将在某个共享对象或某个临界区上操作，
and we don't want to have them interfere with each other and cause problems.
我们不想让它们相互干扰并造成问题。
And the, the two types of problems you could have are logical correctness and physical correctness,
你可能会遇到的两种问题是逻辑正确性和物理正确性，
and I think I mentioned this last week as well.
我想我上周也提到过这个。
So the logical correctness, the idea is that,
所以逻辑正确性的想法是，
if I insert a key into my B+ tree,
如果我把一个键插入到我的 B+ 树中，
I insert key 5
我插入键 5 ，
and then if I come back and I try to look for key 5,
然后如果我回来，试着查找键 5 ，
I should see it.
我应该会看到它。
Well, the other example I said was,
好的，我说的另一个例子是，
if I delete key 5
如果我删除键 5 ，
and I come back and try to look for key 5,
然后我回来尝试查找键 5 ，
again, I shouldn't see it, right.
我应该看不到它。
So, at a logical level,
所以，在逻辑层面上，
that we want to make sure that,
我们希望确保，
we're seeing the things we should see in our data structures.
我们看到的是我们应该在数据结构中看到的东西。
The thing that we care about in today's class is the physical correctness,
我们在今天的课程中关心的是物理正确性，
meaning how do we ensure that,
这意味着我们如何确保，
if we're walking through a hash table or traversing the B+ tree
如果我们遍历哈希表或遍历 B+ 树，
and at some point, we've got to follow a pointer,
在某些点上，我们必须跟随指针，
like like a page ID
比如页面 ID ，
to take us somewhere else,
将我们带到其他地方，
that page ID is is correct,
那个页面 ID 是正确的，
like it's not going to take us to, you know, a table page that has a bunch of garbage in it.
比如它不会把我们带到一个有一堆垃圾的表页。
Because what happens if if you go follow a page
因为如果跟随一个页面，
and you start looking at data, that doesn't look like you expect to look like,
并开始查看这些看起来并不像你希望看到的数据，
you're going to have a seg fault,
那样会出现段错误，
because you're going to try to read past some buffer
因为你要尝试读取一些过去的缓冲区，
or things, things are gonna, things are to break
或者东西会崩溃，
or you get corrupted data.
或者获得损坏的数据。
So again, logical correctness, we'll worry about later, after midterm,
所以再次，逻辑正确性，我们会在期中考试之后担心，
today's class is really about physical correctness.
今天的课程是关于物理正确性的。
So I first want to describe,
所以，我首先想要介绍，
go over quickly of what latches are again
快速介绍一下什么是 latch ，
and how do you actually implement them inside of our database system.
以及如何在我们的数据库系统中实现它们。
And again, the takeaway here is that,
再次，这里的要点是，
ideally we don't want to rely on what the operating system
理想情况下，我们不想依赖操作系统，
gives us in terms of latches.
在 latch 方面提供给我们的东西。
Then we'll see a simplified example of
然后我们将看到一个简单的例子，
of how to do hash table latching,
如何进行哈希表 latch ，
let's say most our time doing B+ tree latching,
我们大部分时间都在进行 B+ 树 latch ，
and we'll see a basic version and an optimized version,
我们将看到一个基本版本和一个优化版本，
and then we'll finish off talking how to handle leaf node scans.
然后我们将以讨论如何处理叶子节点扫描结束。
Okay?
好的？
All right, so I think I showed this slide before
好的，我想我之前展示了这张幻灯片，
and again I just want to revisited again
我想再次重温一下，
this [] between locks and latches.
lock 和 latch 之间的[]。
And again, if you're coming from the OS world or distributed world,
再说一次，如果你来自操作系统世界或分布式世界，
they, they might mean,
他们可能是指，
when I say latch, they might think lock, right.
当我说 latch 时，他们可能会认为是 lock 。
But in database,
但是在数据库中，
that's what we care about mostly my life in, in this course,
这是我们在这门课中最关心的，
so we need to make sure,
所以我们需要确保，
we understand what we're talking about
我们理解我们在说什么，
when we say lock versus the latch.
当我们说到 lock 与 latch 时。
So a lock is going to be this high level, primitive, protection primitive,
所以 lock 是一个高级的保护原语，
that allows us to protect the logical contents of our database,
它允许我们保护数据库的逻辑内容，
like a tuple, a database, a table, right,
比如一个 tuple ，一个数据库，一个表，
and the,
还有，
when we acquire one of these locks,
当我们获得这些 lock 中的一个时，
the transaction will hold that lock for the duration of that transaction,
事务将在该事务的持续时间内持有这个 lock ，
it's not always true,
这并不总是正确的，
we'll see examples where we can release locks, maybe early,
我们将看到可以提前释放锁的示例，
but for our purposes today,
但出于我们今天的目的，
we'll assume that's the case.
我们假设情况就是这样。
And then there'll be some higher level mechanism within our,concurrency protocol,
然后在我们的并发协议中会有一些更高级别的机制，
that's going to ensure that we don't have any deadlocks,
来确保我们不会有任何死锁，
and then if a deadlock does arise,
然后，如果真的出现死锁，
then the the databases will have a mechanism
那么数据库将具有一种机制，
to be able to roll back the changes that the transaction made
能够回滚事务所做的更改，
to make it look as if, you know, it didn't make any changes,
使其看起来就像没有进行任何更改，
so we don't, we don't have any partial updates.
所以我们没有任何部分更新。
Today we're focused on latches
今天我们关注的是 latch ，
and so the latches are going to be the low level primitives,
所以 latch 是低级原语，
that we used to protect critical sections in our, in our data structures,
我们用来保护我们的数据结构中的临界区，
from one worker, you know, against, against another.
从一个 worker 到另一个 worker 。
And so the, the duration of the lifetime, that we're going to hold a latch is going to be very short,
所以，我们将持有 latch 的生命周期将非常短，
like go like think a critical section,
比如，考虑一个临界区，
I'm going to go take a latch on a page,
我在页面上放一个 latch ，
make some change,
做一些修改，
and then release that latch immediately.
然后立即释放那个 latch 。
And, because it's going to be very simple,
因为这将是非常简单的，
we minimize amount of bookkeeping, we're taking for these latches,
我们最大限度地减少了为这些 latch 所做的记账的数量，
we don't want to have, we don't,
我们不想拥有，
the database system is not going to automatically roll back any changes for us,
数据库系统不会自动为我们回滚任何更改，
we don't avoid deadlocks
我们不会避免死锁，
and try to not make any changes
我们不会进行任何更改，
unless we acquire the latch for something,
除非我们获得了某个东西的 latch ，
so that we don't have to roll things back,
这样我们就不必回滚，
we would have minimal coordination
我们将有最小限度的协调，
between the, between the different workers running at the same time.
在同时运行的不同 worker 之间。
Whereas in the lock case I,
而在锁的情况下，
I'm jumping ahead,
我跳到了前面，
but there will be a table literally internally called a lock table,
但是会有一个表，在内部被称为锁表，
and you go look in there,
你去看看里面，
you can see who holds locks for different objects,
你可以看到对于不同的对象谁持有锁，
in latches, we don't want to maintain any of that,
在 latch 中，我们不想维护这些，
because that's so expensive,
因为这太昂贵了，
relative to the amount of work we want to do
相对于我们希望的工作量，
within a critical section in our data structures.
在数据结构中的临界区中。
So there's this, there's this table,
所以有这张表，
I also, like from the the book I recommended last time,
来自上一次我推荐的书，
from this guy, the B tree book,
来自这个人的 B 树书，
when again he shows this change between the locks versus latches
他展示了锁和 latch 之间的变化，
and the way to sort to read this table is,
看这个表的方法是，
within a column you read down
在一个列中，向下看，
and say, you know what the thing is protecting,
你知道它在保护什么，
how is protecting it
如何保护它，
and the different ways it's protecting things.
以及保护东西的不同方法。
So for example,
例如，
a lock is going to separate transactions from each other
一个锁将事务彼此分开，
and it's going to protect the logical database contents
它将保护逻辑数据库内容，
pages or sorry, tuples, tables, databases,
页面，抱歉， tuple ，表，数据库,
and we can hold them for the entire length of the transaction,
我们可以在整个事务期间持有它们，
we'll talk about modes in a second,
我们将在稍后讨论模式，
we can take a lock for an object in different modes,
我们可以在不同的模式下给对象加锁，
like exclusive, shared, intention, updates,
比如独占、共享、意图、更新，
we'll get, we'll get there later,
我们稍后将到达那里，
and that the database system provide either deadlock detection or deadlock prevention mechanisms
数据库系统提供死锁检测或死锁预防机制，
built in to avoid these problems,
内置以避免这些问题，
and then again, these are the mechanisms to do this.
这些都是实现这个的机制。
And then the information that we're to keep track of, what locks are being held
然后我们要跟踪的什么锁被持有的信息，
is being kept in a lock manager, a centralized data structure.
被保存在锁管理器中，一个集中的数据结构。
Today, again, we're focused on latches,
今天，我们专注于 latch ，
so latch, latches are going to protect workers from each other,
所以 latch 将保护 worker 免受彼此的干扰，
this will be only for in memory data structures,
这将仅在内存数据结构中使用，
so like this is literally for the, you know, B+ trees in memory,
所以这是字面上的， B+ 树在内存中，
but once, you know if if if a page within our B+ tree gets flushed out the disk,
但是，一旦 B+ 树中的一个页面刷新到磁盘中，
I wouldn't hold the latch for that thing,
我就不会持有那个东西的 latch ，
when it goes out to disk,
当它到磁盘上时，
because it's meaningless.
因为这是没有意义的。
It's protecting the critical sections,
它是在保护临界区，
there's only be two modes,
只有两种模式，
we can hold our latches in, read and write,
我们可以持有 latch 在读写中，
and the way we're going to handle deadlocks is through coding discipline,
我们处理死锁的方法是通过编码准则，
us as the system developers
我们作为系统开发人员，
have to write good code to make sure there's no deadlocks.
必须编写良好的代码来确保没有死锁。
Easier said than done sure,
说起来容易做起来难，
but like there's not going to be something, some other part of the system,
但不会有什么系统的其他部分，
that's going to bail us out.
会帮助我们摆脱困境。
And we're going to keep the information about these latches
我们将保留有关这些 latch 的信息，
are actually embedded in the data structure itself,
实际上嵌入在数据结构本身中，
so there won't be a centralized, centralized thing.
所以不会有一个集中的东西。
Again, this makes more sense,
再次，这会更有意义，
when we start walking through the different data structure types,
当我们开始讨论不同的数据结构类型时，
and so the lock stuff,
关于锁的内容，
we'll cover after midterm in lecture 15.
我们将在期中考试后的第 15 节课讨论。
So our latches only have two modes,
所以我们的 latch 只有两种模式，
it can be read mode or a write mode.
它可以是读模式或写模式。
So read mode, there are commutative operations,
所以，读模式，在交替操作中，
where you can have multiple workers take a latch in read mode at the same time,
你可以让多个 worker 同时在读模式下获取 latch ，
because, you know whatever they're doing
因为，无论它们正在做什么，
isn't going to, you know, isn't going to break whatever the data structure is,
都不会破坏任何数据结构，
it calls, calls any conflicts, right.
引起冲突。
If I need, if two workers need to read the same page,
如果两个 worker 需要读取同一个页面，
and I can take that in read mode,
我可以在读取模式下进行，
well, that that doesn't, they're not do any right,
它们没有做任何写入，
it doesn't break anything,
它不会破坏任何东西，
so I can go ahead and have them both run at the same time.
这样我就可以继续，让它们同时运行。
Write mode or exclusive mode is,
写模式或独占模式是，
when you know one thread is wants to access the object and actually make changes to it,
当你知道一个线程想要访问对象并对其进行更改时，
and I don't want any other threads to run the same to operate on my object at the same time,
我不希望任何其他线程同时运行相同的线程来操作我的对象，
so only one, only one worker can hold the latch in write mode
所以，只有一个 worker 可以将 latch 保持在写模式下，
and that blocks everyone else else out, right.
这会阻止其他所有线程进入。
And a really simple compatibility matrix will look like this.
一个非常简单的兼容性矩阵将看起来像这样。
If I have a read mode,
如果我有一个读模式，
if I have a latch in read mode,
如果我有一个处于读模式的 latch ，
if someone wants to get a latch in read mode,
如果有人想要在读模式下获得一个 latch ，
I can do that, that's allowed,
我可以这样做，这是允许的，
but any other combination,
但是任何其他组合，
where at least one of the latches either holds it in write mode
如果至少有一个 latch 将其保持在写模式，
or wants to get it in write mode,
或希望使其进入写模式，
I have to deny that.
我必须拒绝这个。
So again, going back to what I say before about coding discipline,
再次，回到我之前所说的编码规则，
like the stupidest thing to do is to take every latch in write mode,
最愚蠢的事情就是让每一个 latch 在写模式，
even though you're only going to read it,
即使你只会读取它，
it'll protect all your data structures,
它将保护你的所有数据结构，
but like, you know, basically going to get relegated to a single thread system,
但是，基本上会被降级到单线程系统，
and likewise, if I take my latch in read mode,
同样，如果我在读模式下使用 latch ，
but I start making changes to whatever it's protecting,
但我开始对它所保护的东西进行更改，
then that's, that's our fault, that's the programmer's fault,
那就是我们的错，这是程序员的错，
and the system crashes, that's on us.
然后系统就会崩溃，这是我们的责任。
And there isn't any,
而这里没有任何，
without getting into verifiable languages,
如果不进入可验证的语言，
there isn't really any mechanism in C++ or Rust,
在 C++ 或 Rust 中没有任何机制，
that's going to protect us for these things, right,
可以保护我们免受这些事情的影响，
because the compiler can't know.
因为编译器无法知道。
So let's look how you want to implement latches.
所以，让我们来看看你想要如何实现 latch 。
So, ideally, we want a latch that has small memory footprint,
所以，理想情况下，我们需要一个内存占用较小的 latch ，
because we don't want to store a lot of additional metadata for our latch,
因为我们不想为 latch 存储大量附加元数据，
because we're these be embedded in the data structure itself
因为我们希望这些元数据嵌入到数据结构本身中，
and ideally we want to have it be,
理想情况下，我们希望它成为，
when there's no contention in the system,
当系统中没有争用时，
meaning there's no two threads or workers trying to acquire latch at the same time,
意味着没有两个线程或 worker 试图同时获取 latch ，
we want to go as fast as possible with minimal overhead,
我们希望以最小的开销尽可能快地运行，
I acquire the latch and do my thing right away.
我拿到 latch ，马上做我的事。
If we have to,
如果我们必须，
we can't get the latch we need,
我们不能获取我们需要的 latch ，
then we have to make a decision
然后我们必须决定，
of how long we should wait
我们应该等待多长时间，
and how we want to wait,
以及我们想要如何等待，
and we'll see different scenarios of how we want to do this.
我们将看到我们想要如何做到这个的不同场景。
And ideally, also too, we, we, we don't want to have a bunch of metadata per latch
在理想情况下，我们也不希望每个 latch 都有一堆元数据，
about who's waiting for this latch,
关于谁在等待这个 latch ，
because that's now basically a cue for every single latch,
因为这基本上是每一个 latch 的提示，
you could have in your data structure,
你可以包含在你的数据结构中，
and I think of like a giant B+ tree with a billion entries,
比如有一棵巨大的 B+ 树，有十亿个条目，
how many, how many pages you're going to have in there,
你要在里面放多少页，
each of those could have now their own priority queue, right.
其中每一个都有自己的优先队列。
So again, coming from the database world,
所以，再次，来自数据库世界，
we say we don't,
我们说我们不，
we don't want to rely on the OS to do any of these things,
我们不想依赖操作系统来做任何这些事情，
but then the OS people say,
但操作系统人员表示，
the database system don't know know what they're doing
数据库系统不知道他们在做什么，
and they should not be implementing their own latches,
他们不应该实现自己的 latch ，
and you can see this in the the Linux mailing list,
你可以在 Linux 邮件列表中看到这个，
so here's a post from Linus saying,
所以这里有一个来自 Linus 的帖子说，
like oh yeah, like you don't, you should not be writing your own latching thing,
哦，是的，你不应该写你自己的 latch 东西，
and it basically says here,
它基本上是这样说的，
like you should not use spinlocks,
比如你不应该使用自旋锁，
that I'll explain that is in a second,
我会在稍后解释，
in user space, that's us,
在用户空间，这就是我们，
where the database system running a user space,
数据库系统运行在用户空间，
says you should not be using spinlocks, so you roll yourself,
说你不应该使用自旋锁，让自己自旋，
unless you know what you're doing
除非你知道你在做什么，
and the chances are you know what you're doing is low.
而且你做的变更是[底层]的。
He's wrong, despite being Linus.
他错了，尽管他是 Linus 。
All right, so I'm going to go through three basic implementations
好的，我将介绍三个基本实现，
of of how to implement latches.
关于如何实现 latch 。
There's more advanced ones,
还有更先进的，
like the ParkingLot stuff from Apple,
比如 Apple 的 ParkingLot ，
this is probably the best one to use right now,
这可能是目前使用的最好的一个，
and then there MCS Locks,
然后有 MCS 锁，
which is a queuing thing,
它是队列的东西，
we'll cover in in the advanced class,
我们将在高级课程中讨论，
but for our purposes here,
但就我们这里的目的而言，
we don't need to know this,
我们不需要知道这个，
but we need to understand the basic implementation of what latches are actually doing,
但我们需要了解 latch 实际做什么的基本实现，
so that when you start sprinkling them in your code,
当你开始将它们分散在代码中时，
you understand the ramifications of them.
你了解了它们的后果。
You mean pthread mutex,
你是说 pthread mutex ，
we'll get to that in a second, yes.
我们很快就会讲到这个，是的。
Her question is,
她的问题是，
what's wrong with C++ mutex.
C++ mutex 有什么问题。
So if you call mutex at C++,
所以，如果在 C++ 中调用 mutex ，
what do you actually get?
你实际上得到了什么？
Yeah, but who's implementing that?
是的，但是谁实现了那个？
Pthread, but how does a pthread work?
Pthread ，但是 pthread 是如何工作的？
Two more slides, okay.
再多几张幻灯片，好的。
All right, so, maybe this the slide.
好的，所以，也许这就是那个幻灯片。
All right, so the most basic,
好的，所以最基本的，
take it back, this is database world,
回来一下，这是数据库世界，
we'll talk OS one next.
下一个我们再讨论操作系统的。
So the most basic latch you implement is
所以你实现的最基本的 latch 是，
called a test-and-set, test-and-set spin lock,
调用 test-and-set 自旋锁，
sorry, a spin lock,
抱歉，自旋锁，
and I realize I'm calling spin lock when really latches.
我意识到我调用的是自旋锁，其实应该是自旋 latch 。
But this is the most simplest way to implement this is,
但这是实现这一点最简单的方法，
because it literally is a 64 bit memory address,
因为它实际上是一个 64 位的内存地址，
that you're just going to do atomic compare and swap on
你只需要做原子比较和交换，
to see whether you can set it,
看看你是否可以设置它，
and if you can't set it,
如果你不能设置它，
then you spin and keep trying to set it over and over again,
那么你就旋转，一直试着一遍又一遍地设置它，
like the code literally look like this,
代码看起来像这样，
I declare a an atomic boolean,
我声明一个原子布尔型，
this is just a syntactic sugar for declaring something that's atomic,
这只是一个声明原子的东西的语法糖，
and then now I have this, my latch here
然后现在我有了这个，我的 latch 在这里，
and I call it test-and-set
我调用 test-and-set ，
and literally just trying to set a check
字面上只是试图设置一个检查，
to see whether it's current value 0,
看看它是否为当前的值为 0 ，
if, if if, if yes, then I can set the 1
如果是的，我可以设置 1 ，
and I can do that in a single, single instruction atomically,
我可以在单个指令中原子地完成该操作，
so it's not like if, then this, then that,
所以这不像是 if, then this, then that ，
somebody else can come swoop in and change it before I before I can,
其他人可以突然出现，并在我之前修改它，
it literally one instruction to go apply this change,
它是字面意义上的一条指令来应用这个改变，
and if I can't get it, then I just spin,
如果我拿不到，我就旋转，
because we're doing this in the database, database level at user space,
因为我们是在用户空间的数据库级别中操作，
we can decide whether, how many times we want to retry,
我们可以决定是要重试多少次，
whether we want to yield the thread to the OS
还是要让出线程给操作系统，
or abort ourselves and restart.
还是放弃并重新开始。
All right, why is this bad?
好的，为什么这很糟糕？
What's that, wait, you said, busy wait.
是什么，等待，你说的，忙等待。
So you're basically spinning the cycle, spinning the CPU,
所以你基本上是在旋转周期，旋转 CPU ，
check, check, check, over and over again.
检查，检查，检查，一遍又一遍。
I could put maybe like,
我可以这么说，
I could put a exponential back off to say,
我可以把指数放回去说，
okay, I tried to get,
好的，我试着获取，
I couldn't get it, wait one millisecond, two milliseconds, four milliseconds, right.
我获取不到，等一毫秒，两毫秒，四毫秒。
Actually, the, so that's a challenge,
事实上，这是一个挑战，
that you're just spinning over and over again,
你只是一遍又一遍地旋转，
another problem is going to be cache coherence traffic, right.
另一个问题将是缓存一致性[流量]。
So again, assuming I have a two socket CPU,
所以，假设我有一个双插槽 CPU ，
the latch I'm trying to acquire is over here on this this NUMA region,
我想要获取的 latch 在这个 NUMA 区域上，
know what NUMA is, Non Uniform Memory Access,
知道 NUMA 是什么，非一致内存访问，
basically like if I have two sockets in my,
比如我的 [] 中有两个插槽，
two, two sockets or two or more sockets on my motherboard,
我的主板上有两个插槽或更多个插槽，
each CPU sockets is going to have DRAM that's close to it
每个 CPU 插槽都会有接近它的 DRAM ，
and it's really fast to talk to that,
与之交互很快，
but I can also talk to memory that's over on another socket,
但我也可以与另一个插座上的内存交互，
and it's call it a NUMA region,
它称为 NUMA 区域，
but that that traffic is much slower,
但是这个流量要慢得多，
because I got to go over this interconnect between one socket to the other, right,
因为我必须通过一个插槽到另一个插槽之间的互连，
And so Intel, they do a lot of work
所以， Intel 做了很多工作，
to make sure when you write programs
以确保当你编写程序时，
you don't know and and don't technically have to know where memory actually is physically located,
你不知道，从技术上讲，你不需要知道内存的实际位置，
but of course, now you could have your program access something that's on another socket
但是当然，现在你可以让你的程序访问另一个插槽上的东西，
and it gets really slow
它变得非常慢，
and the hardware tries to play games and move things around for you
硬件试图使用技巧，为你移动东西，
try to speed things up,
试图加快速度，
we can ignore that for now,
我们可以暂时忽略这个，
and for this class, we don't have to worry about NUMA,
对于这门课，我们不必担心 NUMA ，
I just want to explain that.
我只是想解释一下。
This, this, a worker running on this, this CPU over here
这个 CPU 上运行的 worker ，
wants to acquire the latch in this other socket CPU memory,
想要获取这个另一个插槽 CPU 内存中的 latch ，
so it's going to keep spinning and over it again,
所以它会不停地旋转，
but now it's all this traffic over this interconnect
但是现在，这个互连上的所有流量
that's going to slow my entire database system down.
将使我的整个数据库系统变慢。
So this is inefficient,
所以这是低效的，
because I'm spinning,
因为我在旋转，
but also like the traffic on the actual hardware itself is expensive.
而且实际硬件上的流量本身也很昂贵。
So now her question is,
所以现在她的问题是，
you know why, what's wrong
为什么，出了什么问题，
or how does actually the C++ mutex actually work?
或者 C++ mutex 实际上是如何工作的？
So this is called a blocking mutex,
所以，这被称为阻塞 mutex ，
it's the easiest thing to use,
它是最容易使用的，
because it's built in C++,
因为它是内置在 C++ 中的，
basically, you acquire and release,
基本上，你获取和释放，
there's not a lot of mechanisms in it
它没有太多的机制，
and the way you use it, it's sort of like this,
你使用它的方式，就像这样，
you lock it and unlock,
你对它加锁，再解锁，
do whatever you want in the middle.
在中间做你想做的任何事情。
So I asked her, how is this thing actually implemented,
所以我问她，这个东西是如何实现的，
is anybody know,
有人知道吗，
so if you call std::mutex,
所以，如果你调用 std::mutex ，
what do you get in C++,
你在 C++ 中得到了什么，
pthread_mutex,
pthread_mutex ，
how is pthread_mutex implemented,
pthread_mutex 是如何实现的，
it's called futex it's in Linux,
它调用 futex ，它在 Linux 中，
everybody heard futex before,
大家之前都听说过 futex 吗，
fast userspace mutex.
快速用户空间 mutex 。
So the way it works is.
所以它的工作方式是。
It has the spin lock that I just showed in the last slide,
它有我在上一张幻灯片中展示的自旋锁，
in user space, they'll have their own little test and set thing you can do,
在用户空间，他们会有自己的 test-and-set ，你可以做，
but if you can't, if you try to acquire it and you can't,
如果你试图获取它，但你不能，
then you fall back to a heavy heavyweight mutex inside the kernel,
然后，你将退回到内核中的重量级 mutex ，
so, so if if no one holds a latch with a futex, I try to acquire it,
所以，如果没有人持有一个 latch ，有我会尝试获取的 futex ，
If no one holds it,
如果没有人持有它，
then I just do a compare and swap real real fast in user space,
那么我只需在用户空间中快速进行比较和交换，
and I'm done,
我就完成了，
and my program, my thread keeps running,
我的程序，我的线程一直在运行，
if I can't get it,
如果我不能得到它，
then the OS takes control of us
那么操作系统从我们接管控制，
and we go down now into the kernel
我们现在进入内核，
and then we get descheduled,
然后我们会被取消调度，
because it knows that I can't run
因为它知道我不能运行，
until the thing I'm waiting for is available.
直到我等待的东西可用。
But what's down in the kernel,
但是内核里到底有什么，
How they keep track of threads,
他们是如何跟踪线程的，
what's that.
是什么。
Sorry, say that again,
抱歉，再说一遍，
blocking queue, but like, what,
阻塞队列，但是什么，
there's also,
还有，
there's the scheduler has its own hash table
调度器有自己的哈希表
to keep track of what threads are running,
来跟踪哪些线程正在运行，
so they use their own latches to protect that data structure.
所以它们使用自己的 latch 来保护数据结构。
So if I can't acquire this,
所以，如果我不能获得这个，
I go down in the kernel
我会进入内核，
and I get descheduled
我会被取消调度，
and that's very, very expensive,
这是非常非常昂贵的，
syscalls are expensive,
系统调用是昂贵的，
we want to avoid them, right.
我们想避免它们。
All right, so this is just the diagram like this.
好的，就是像这样的图表。
So again, I have my two, two workers running different sockets,
所以，同样，我有两个 worker 运行在不同的插槽上，
they both try to [] at the same time,
它们都试图在同一时间[]，
one of them will get the userspace latch,
其中一个将获得用户空间 latch ，
the other guy tries to go down and get the OS latch
另一个试图下去拿操作系统 latch ，
and they get, they get descheduled, right.
它们被取消调度。
And again, this is, this is slow,
再次，这是缓慢的，
because anytime you involve the OS, this is bad.
因为任何时候你涉及到操作系统，这是糟糕的。
So the last two, first two latches I showed you,
所以我展示的前两个 latch ，
they didn't really have modes,
它们并没有模式，
it was just all or nothing,
只是全有或全无，
and so the way you implement this in a,
所以，你实现这个的方式，
in in in plus with the reader-writer latch,
加上读写 latch ，
you can use shared_mutex,
你可以使用 shared_mutex ，
I think we we do the read write lock in in BusTub,
我想我们在 BusTub 做读写锁，
which is just pthread read-write lock.
只是一个 pthread 读写锁。
And the way this basically works is that,
这个工作的方式是，
the latch itself is going to have its own priority queues,
latch 本身将有自己的优先队列，
its own counterters, keep track of like how many threads are waiting,
它自己的计数器，记录有多少线程在等待，
you actually can find the scheduling policy for the the, the, the the latch itself.
实际上，你可以找到 latch 本身的调度策略。
So the idea here is that,
所以这里的想法是，
if I have a, a reader thread comes along
如果我有一个读器线程出现，
and once acquire the latch,
一旦获取 latch ，
I go check to see whether anybody waiting for the read latch
我去检查是否有人在等待读 latch
or the latch in read mode or write mode,
或 latch 在读模式或写模式，
if it's available,
如果它可用，
then I increment my counter
那么我递增我的计数器，
to say somebody's holding the the read latch now
说现在有人在持有读 latch ，
and I go ahead and do whatever I want.
我继续做我想做的事情。
And now if anybody else comes along,
现在，如果其他人也出现，
also wants acquire the read mode,
也想获取读模式，
the system knows I'm,
系统知道我，
the the latch knows I'm in read mode right now,
latch 知道我现在处于读模式，
so it can let the other guy run as well.
这样它就可以让其他人也运行。
But now if if a write latch write worker comes along,
但是现在，如果出现写入 worker ，
tries acquire the latch,
尝试获取 latch ，
we have two read, read workers already holding the latch in read mode,
我们有两个读取 worker 已经持有 latch 在读模式，
so it's going to have to stall
所以，它将不得不停止，
and they maintain an internal priority queue
它们维护一个内部优先级队列，
to keep track of what threads are waiting for this.
以跟踪哪些线程正在等待这个。
So then, depending on the policy,
然后，根据策略，
you can configure in the latch,
你可以在 latch 中配置，
if another thread comes along,
如果出现另一个线程，
then once again in read mode
然后再次在读模式下，
and in theory I could, I could acquire it,
理论上，我可以获取它，
because it's commutative with all the other latches or the workers that hold it in read mode,
因为它与所有其他持有在读模式下的 worker 是可交换的，
I could it query right away,
我可以马上查询，
but you can set the policy,
但是你可以设置策略，
to say I know another thread is waiting for it in write mode,
我知道另一个线程正在以读模式等待它，
so let me go ahead and put it to sleep, right.
所以让我继续，并将它睡眠。
And in C++,
在 C++ 中，
I think they're doing this all in in userspace,
我认为它们都是在用户空间中完成的，
not, not down in the kernel,
不是在内核中，
but, but when you have to then block and wait for the require the latch you're looking for,
但是，当你不得不阻塞并等待你要寻找的 latch 时，
then that's going to be an OS kernel, OS mutex,
那将是一个操作系统 mutex ，
which we don't want to do.
这是我们不想做的。
So the, again, I just showing you a high level overview
所以，我刚刚向你们高级别的概述，
of the the the test-and-set operation, compare-and-swap,
test-and-set 操作， compare-and-swap ，
is the basing building block that you used to build more complicated latch primitives,
是你用来构建更复杂的 latch 原语的基础构建块。
And depending on that,
取决于这个，
whether you want the OS to do it or not,
你是否希望操作系统这样做，
most systems, most,
大多数系统，
most bigger database systems, the enterprise ones,
大多数大的数据库系统，企业级的，
will not rely on the OS for anything,
将不会依赖于操作系统的任何东西，
and it's a combination for portability,
它是可移植性的[组合]，
and also it's just faster to avoid the OS
而且它避免操作系统是更快地，
and Linus goes wrong.
Linus 是错的。
Alright, so now let's,
好的，那么现在让我们，
yes.
是的。
I just want to clarify,
我只想确认，
is the blocking mutex also built on test-and-set?
阻塞 mutex 也是建立在 test-and-set 上的吗？
The question is, is blocking mutex [] that build on test-and-set,
问题是，是否阻塞 mutex 建立在 test-and-set 之上，
all of them are, yes,
所有这些都是，是的，
yeah, like that's the,
是的，就像，
you ever know what compare-and-swap is?
你们知道什么是 compare-and-swap 吗？
No, okay, I have slides, one slide.
不，好的，我有幻灯片，一张幻灯片。
All right, so compare-and-swap is this atomic instruction,
好的， compare-and-swap 是一种原子指令，
that, that modern CPUs provide,
现代 CPU 提供的，
that allow you to check a memory location
允许你检查内存位置，
to see whether it's a current,
以查看它是否是当前的，
whether the current value of that memory address is what you expected it to be,
该内存地址的当前值是否为你预期的值，
and if it is, then I can go ahead
如果是，那么我可以继续，
and overwrite it with my new value
用我的新值覆盖它，
in, in a single instruction,
在一条单独的指令中，
if you had to do this in C++ code
如果你必须在 C++ 代码中这样做，
to be like if the value equals this,
比如，如果这个值等于这个，
then set it to that,
那么把它设置为那个，
but again, if that was just the actual instructions to do that,
但是，如果这只是完成这一任务的实际指令，
that would be multiple instructions,
那将是多条指令，
and by the time you go check to see whether that value is,
当你去检查这个值是否，
you know, is the flag set to true,
标志是否设置为 true 时，
by the time you go and then go update it,
当你去更新它的时候，
somebody else might have [] in and sneaked in before you did and update before before.
其他人可能已经在你之前偷偷进入并在之前更新了。
And so on modern CPUs,
所以，在现代 CPU 上，
you can do this in a single instruction,
你可以在一条单独的指令中做到这个，
that's atomic, to guarantee that,
这是原子的，保证，
by when you check it and set it,
当你检查并设置它时，
no one else can get in before you do.
其他人不能比你先进去。
And then that's the basic primitive, allows us to do more complicated things.
这是基本的原语，允许我们做更复杂的事情。
So there's a bunch of different intrinsics in, in, in C and C++
所以在 C 和 C++ 中，有一堆不同的内在函数，
you can use for this, right,
你可以用来做这个，
they have different versions of this,
它们有不同的版本，
like some like if you, if the test-and-set can succeed or the compare-and-swap succeed,
比如，如果 test-and-set 成功，或者 compare-and-swap 成功，
they'll return back the old value or the new value or true and false,
它们将返回旧值或新值或 ture 和 false ，
but they're all basically doing the same thing,
但它们基本上都在做同样的事情，
so let's say in this case here,
所以，在这种情况下，
for this intrinsic,
对于这个内部函数，
I'm saying here's the address I want to check
我说这是我想检查的地址，
and assume it's a 64 bit integer,
假设它是一个 64 位整数，
here's the value that I want to see whether is currently set to,
这是我想要查看当前是否设置的值，
and then if it is, here's the value I want to set it to right now.
如果是，这是我希望现在设置的值。
So we jump to this memory address here,
所以我们跳到这个内存地址，
it's 20, 20 equals 20, yes,
它是 20 ， 20 等于 20 ，是的，
then I go ahead and overwrite with 30.
然后，我继续，并用 30 覆盖。
Pretty simple,
很简单，
but that's again, that's the building block, we need to have all,
但是，这是我们需要的构建块，
you know, to build all our more complicated latches.
来构建所有更复杂的 latch 。
I don't know when this compare-and-swap stuff was added,
我不知道这个 compare-and-swap 的东西是什么时候加的，
I think it was like the late 90s,
我认为是在 90 年代末，
at least in 1986.
至少在 1986 。
So we good.
我们好了吗。
Okay, cool, all right.
好的，酷，好的。
So let's see how we can do this for hash tables now,
现在，让我们看看如何对哈希表做这个，
or use latch on hash tables.
或者在哈希表上使用 latch 。
So hash table is going to be easy to support,
所以哈希表将很容易被支持，
because assuming linear probe hashing is that,
因为，假设线性探测哈希是，
there's only certain many ways you can actually access the hash table,
你只有确定的很多方法可以访问哈希表，
I hash, assuming it's linear, linear, linear probe hashing,
假设它是线性探测哈希，
I hash to some location into my hash hash array or a hash table
我哈希到我的哈希数组或哈希表中的某个位置，
and I then I scan down from top to down
然后我从上到下扫描，
to looking for the entries, I'm looking, you know, that I need, right.
寻找我寻找的条目，我所需要的。
And in this case here,
在这个例子中，
because the threads are all moving in the same direction,
因为所有线程都朝着相同的方向移动，
like going top down,
从上到下，
even though they may start at different locations in the hash table,
即使它们可能从哈希表中的不同位置开始，
I can't have any deadlocks,
我不会有任何死锁，
because there isn't one thread going top down, another thread going bottom up, right.
因为没有一个线程自上而下，另一个线程自下而上。
So, the question is going to be to,
所以，问题将会是，
what granularity do we do,
我们要做的是什么粒度，
we want to have our latch to protect our data structure,
我们希望有我们的 latch 来保护我们的数据结构，
because that's going to determine the amount of parallelism we'll be able to support.
因为这将决定我们能够支持的并行度。
For this lecture,
对于这节课，
we're going to ignore how to handle resizing the table,
我们将忽略如何处理表的大小调整，
the way, the simplest way to handle that is,
处理这一问题的最简单方法是，
you have sort of a write latch that protects the, the access to the data structure itself,
你有一个写入 latch 来保护对数据结构本身的访问，
so if if I get full and I need to double the size of it,
所以如果我满了，我需要把它的大小增加一倍，
I just switch that latch into write mode
我只需将 latch 切换到写入模式，
and then do my, my resizing
然后进行我的大小调整，
and that prevents everybody else from coming in,
这样就会阻止其他人进入，
that's the easiest way to do this.
这是做这个最简单的方法。
So the scopes of our latches can either be within a page or slot,
所以，我们的 latch 的作用域可以在 page 或 slot ，
and again, this is going to determine amount of parallelism we have,
再次，这将决定我们的并行度，
so obviously when a page latch is going to protect the entire page itself with a latch,
所以，很明显，页面 latch 用 latch 保护整个页面本身，
and no matter whether you want to read one entry or all the entries in the page,
无论你想要读取页面中的一个条目还是所有条目，
you would, you would hold a latch on the entire thing.
你都会持有整个内容的 latch 。
The alternative would be, you would have a latch for every single slot in a page,
另一种选择是，页面中的每个单独 slot 都有一个 latch ，
and this is going to allow more fine-grain access,
这将允许更细粒度的访问，
but again, now the challenge is that,
但是，现在的挑战是，
I'm going to take more space,
我要占用更多的空间，
because every single, every single slot needs to have a latch,
因为每个单独的 slot 都需要有一个 latch ，
and now, as I'm scanning through my my hash table,
现在，当我扫描我的哈希表时，
I got to acquire the latch for every single slot as I'm going along.
我在前进的过程中需要获取每个 slot 的 latch 。
So again, there's no free lunch in, in, in systems or in computer science,
所以，再次，在系统或计算机科学领域，没有免费的午餐，
it's either I have a single latch per page,
它要么是我每页只有一个 latch ，
which I only acquire, once for the page,
我只为页面获取一次，
and it doesn't take a lot of space,
它不会占用太多空间，
but then it blocks everyone else out from a the entire page
但它会阻止其他所有在整个页面之外，
or I have it for every single slot.
或者我对每个单独的 slot 有一个（latch）。
So say hash table like this,
假设像这样的哈希表，
T1 wants to come along,
T1 想要[出现]，
thread 1 wants come along and find D,
线程 1 想要出现并查找 D ，
we hash D, we landed this location here,
我们哈希 D ，我们落在这个位置，
we get the entire page in in in write mode,
我们让整个页面处于写模式（这里应该是读模式），
look, try to find the entries that we're looking for by just scanning down,
试着通过向下扫描来找到我们寻找的条目，
but at the same time, another thread wants to come along,
但是同时，另一个线程想要出现，
wants to insert E,
想要插入 E ，
same thing, I hashed to this page,
相同的东西，我哈希到这个页面，
but the latch is already, the page is already latched in in read mode
但是页面已经 latch 在读模式下，
and that's not commutative with, the write mode latch and needs to do the insert,
这与写模式 latch 是不可交换的，需要进行插入，
so we have to stall thread 2,
所以，我们必须停顿线程 2 ，
and again, whether it's spinning in userspace or got rescheduled by the kernel,
无论它是在用户空间旋转还是被内核重新调度，
that depends on your latch implementation.
这取决于你的 latch 实现。
So now when the when thread 1 is done scanning this page,
所以现在，当线程 1 扫描完这个页面时，
it can jump to the next page,
它可以跳到下一页面，
it still holds the latch to the page it started at,
它仍然持有它开始的页面的 latch ，
because it needs to know how to, where to look at next, right,
因为它需要知道如何查看下一页面，
to make sure nobody's moving things around.
确保没人移动东西。
And so we we can then release the latch on page number 1,
然后我们可以释放页面 1 上的 latch ，
acquire the latch on page number 2,
获取页面 2 上的 latch ，
and then now thread 2 can start running
然后线程 2 可以开始运行，
and try to figure out where wants to insert.
并试图找出想要插入的位置。
The same thing once once come down here to do the write,
同样的事情一旦下来这里做写入，
the the read latch is not commutative with the write, write latch,
读 latch 不能与写 latch 交换，
so therefore it has to wait,
所以它必须等待，
then once thread 1 is done,
然后，一旦线程 1 完成，
thread 2 can then acquire the latch and do the update to insert its entry.
线程 2 就可以获取 latch ，并进行更新，插入它的条目。
Yes, question.
是的，问题。
Your question is,
你的问题是，
if I hold, if I hold the, I have a read latch,
如果我持有一个读 latch ，
say there again, sorry.
再说一遍，抱歉。
So going back to like the very beginning here?
所以回到最开始这里？
So again, say this scenario here,
所以，假设这里的场景，
say T2 shows up before T1,
假设 T2 出现在 T1 之前，
and what the race condition you trying to deal with?
那么你想要处理的竞态条件是什么？
Alright, so what you say read, write,
好的，所以你说的读写，
read and then write and then read,
读，然后写，然后读，
like that second read, is that like another find a key?
第二次读，是不是另一个查找键？
But is it wrong?
但这是错的吗？
Yeah, so, so.
是的，所以，所以。
So yeah, so there's,
所以，是的，所以，
there, this is the logical correctness thing, right.
这是逻辑上的正确性。
If say I I I do a SELECT,
如果我做一个 SELECT ，
I run a little SELECT query,
我运行一个小的 SELECT 查询，
that does look up in this hash table
它在这个哈希表中查找，
and I find D right
我找到了 D ，
and, and I get back the answer,
我就得到了答案，
now some other transaction, another thread comes along and deletes D, right,
现在其他事务，另一个线程出现并删除 D ，
and [] in the hash table,
[]在哈希表中，
then, then the first thread again now runs another SELECT query that finds D
然后第一个线程运行另一个 SELECT 查询来查找 D ，
and it doesn't come back with it, right.
并且不会返回它。
From the data structure perspective,
从数据结构的角度来看，
that's fine for what we're talking about today.
这对于我们今天讨论的内容来说是好的。
When we talk about after the midterm,
当我们在期中考试之后讨论，
that's, that's, that's an anomaly of inconsistent reads.
这就是不一致读的反常现象。
And that's something that the mechanism for the system will handle in transaction level,
这是系统的机制将在事务级别处理的事情，
at the low level level of the data structure, we don't care,
在数据结构的低级别，我们不关心，
it's correct,
这是正确的，
who decides what in the order what, what writes we should see or not see,
谁决定我们应该看到或不看到什么写入，
that's a higher level thing that comes later.
这是一个在后面发生的更高层次的事情。
Yes,
是的，
and the great thing about databases or these transactions is like,
关于数据库或这些事务的伟大之处在于，
there's multiple answers that are all technically correct, potentially,
有多个潜在的技术上正确的答案，
but we'll get that later.
但我们会在晚些时候讨论。
No, well, in the specification of SQL,
不，好的，在 SQL 的规范中，
there's, there's a, there's a, there's a description about what is considered correct or not correct at different isolation levels,
有关于在不同的隔离级别上被认为是正确或不正确的描述，
which we haven't covered yet, right,
我们还没有讨论，
and the, the easiest, the most strictest correctness level would be, isolation level be,
最简单、最严格的正确级别是，隔离级别是，
called strict serializable or strong serializable,
称为严格可串行化或强可串行化，
basically means that like,
基本上就是，
whoever comes first should should see
无论谁先来，都应该看到，
the system as if it was running by itself
系统就像它自己运行一样，
and its changes get applied first, right,
它的修改首先得到应用。
and then everything else comes after that.
然后其他的一切都在那之后。
But getting way, way ahead of ourselves, from the database perspective,
但是我们继续，从数据库的角度来看，
I don't care that your thread came in and and deleted D,
我不关心你的线程进入，删除 D ，
look for D, then D got deleted
查找 D ，然后 D 被删除，
and you go to look for it again, it's missing,
然后你再去查找它，它不见了，
that's not the data structures problem,
这不是数据结构的问题，
that's somebody else's problem,
那是别人的问题，
it's our problem, but like, not, not today's lecture.
这是我们的问题，但不是今天的课程。
And it's really hard, yeah.
这真的很难，是的。
Oh, it's why all the NoSQL guys didn't use transactions in the beginning,
哦，这就是为什么所有 NoSQL 的人一开始没有使用事务，
because this is hard, right?
因为这很难。
All right, we'll come to that later.
好的，我们稍后再谈这个。
A lot of things they didn't do, because it's hard,
很多事情他们没有做，因为这很难，
and then they had to do it later.
然后他们不得不在晚些时候这样做。
Alright, again, let me just show you how to do slot latches.
好的，让我演示一下如何使用 slot latch 。
Again, now I have a latch on every single slot itself
同样，现在我在每个 slot 本身都有一个 latch ，
and my hash table.
以及我的哈希表。
So now when I do a find D,
所以现在，当我执行查找 D ，
I get the latch, on the read latch on the slot itself,
我得到 slot 本身的读 latch ，
I can go ahead and read what I'm looking for
我可以继续，读取我查找的内容，
and say this guy now wants to jump to this page,
然后说这个想要跳到这个页面，
he wants to get the write latch on, on C,
他想要获取 C 的写 latch ，
ignore how he found that,
忽略他是如何发现的，
because he hash there.
因为他哈希到那里。
The now when the the first thread tries to get the read latch on the next slot,
现在，当第一个线程试图获取下一个 slot 上的读 latch 时，
he can't,
他不能，
because the other thread has the latch,
因为另一个线程持有 latch ，
so he has a stall,
所以他有一个停滞，
but at this point,
但在这一点，
even though he's going to stall and wait,
即使他停滞并等待，
it's safe for him to release the latch on the previous previous slot,
对他来说，释放前一个 slot 上的 latch 是安全的，
because, he has his,
因为，他有他的，
there's, there's no issue,
这里没有问题，
there's no reason for him to keep holding holding this this latch, right,
他没有理由一直持有这个 latch ，
because he's just going to spin and wait for this thing here
因为他只是旋转，在这里等待这个东西，
and everything's still [] there.
一切都在[]那里。
I mentioned the reorganization of the, of, of the hash table itself,
我提到了哈希表本身的重组，
like, if you have to resize it,
例如，如果你必须调整它的大小，
assume that there's some other latch protecting the entire thing that's in read mode,
假设有一些其他的 latch 在读模式保护整个东西，
so that's okay,
所以这是可以的，
we only set that to write mode,
我们只需要设置为写模式，
if we have to resize the whole thing,
如果我们必须调整整个东西大小，
so, so the global latch for,
所以，全局的 latch ，
T2 would have the global latch in read mode.
T2 将持有全局 latch 在读模式。
Yes.
是的。
No, this is,
不，这是，
just think like it's some offset in some page for our hash table,
把它想象成我们的哈希表的某个页面中的某个偏移量，
so it's all fixed length.
所以它的长度都是固定的。
Yeah.
是的。
So like this.
所以这个。
up the page into more Yeah, correct, yes, yeah,
是的，没错，是的，是的，
basically, do you want fine, fine-grain latches or coarse-grain latches,
基本上你想要细粒度 latch 还是粗粒度 latch ，
that's all it is.
仅此而已。
Okay.
好的。
So this should be pretty straightforward.
所以，这应该是相当简单的。
Let's get to B+ trees,
让我们去 B+ 树，
because this is harder and and more fun.
因为这更难，也更有趣。
So again, just like before,
所以，就像前面一样，
in our hash table and B+ tree,
在我们的哈希表和 B+ 树中，
want to have multiple threads read at the same time.
希望同时有多个线程读取。
The challenge here is now,
这里的挑战现在是，
in the hash table, with linear probing,
在使用线性探测的哈希表中，
the the number of pages was fixed,
页面的数量是固定的，
and the organization of the data structure was fixed,
并且数据结构的组织是固定的，
meaning like, you know, matter,
意思是，
if I, if I create my hash table
如果我创建我的哈希表，
and I have say a million slots,
我说有一百万个 slot ，
it doesn't matter,
这都无关紧要，
whether I have a thousand threads going at it
不管我有一千个线程在它上面，
or one thread going at it,
还是一个线程在它上面，
I'm always going to have a million slots,
我永远都会有一百万个 slot ，
and as a matter,
事实上，
if I have, you know, have a million keys in it or not,
不管我有没有一百万个键，
the data structure is always the same.
数据结构都是一样的。
In a B+ tree,
在 B+ 树中，
says the data structure is, is is self organize or self balancing,
数据结构是自组织或自平衡的，
as I insert things into it,
当我向其中插入内容时，
oh sorry, deleting things from it,
抱歉，删除其中的内容，
It's going to start reorganizing itself.
它将开始自我重组。
So I need to make sure that,
所以，我需要确保，
as I'm reorganizing things, the splits, emerges,
在我重新组织事物时，拆分，合并，
I make sure that, I have to make sure that,
我必须确保，
the data structure is correct.
数据结构是正确的。
All right, so let's see how things can go bad.
好的，让我们看看事情如何变得糟糕。
Say we have a thread here
假设我们这里有一个线程，
and they want to delete key 44 at the bottom,
他们想要删除底部的键 44 ，
so what do I do,
那我该怎么做，
I traverse down and I look at the guidepost markers
我向下遍历，查看路标标记，
to figure out whether I want to go left and right
确定我是否想要向左或向右，
and I reach down to my my leaf node here
然后向下到达我的叶子节点，
and I go ahead and delete it.
然后我继续，并删除它。
But now I have to rebalance,
但现在我必须重新平衡，
I have to do a merge,
我必须做一个合并，
because this leaf node is is less than half full,
因为这个叶子节点不到半满，
so maybe I'll steal an entry from my sibling,
所以也许我会从我的兄弟节点偷走一个条目，
gonna move 41 over, right,
把 41 移过来，
but before I can do that,
但在我这么做之前，
my thread gets descheduleded, right,
我的线程被取消调度，
for whatever reason,
不管出于什么原因，
the OS decided to do something, [] came down,
操作系统决定做一些事情，[]下来，
it doesn't matter, right,
这无关紧要，
my thread's not running anymore.
我的线程不再运行。
So now, while while thread 1 is asleep,
现在，当线程 1 睡眠的时候，
thread 2 comes along
线程 2 出现了，
and they want to find 41
他们想要查找 41 ，
and they start traversing down just like before and they get here, right,
他们开始像以前一样向下遍历，他们到达了这里，
and again, now they look at the guidepost,
再次，现在他们查看路标，
they follow the the,
他们沿着，
they realize they want to go down to the, to the right to node H,
他们意识到他们想要下到节点 H 的右边，
but now it gets descheduled for whatever reason.
但是现在，它被取消调度，无论出于什么原因。
And then thread 1 wakes up, moves 41,
然后线程 1 醒来，移动了 41 ，
T1, T2, thread 2 wakes up,
线程 2 醒来，
goes down to the node, thought it was need of the go to,
下到节点，以为是需要去的，
and now the key's not there.
现在键不在那里了。
Best case scenario,
最好的情况是，
you get a false negative here,
你会得到一个假[]，
worst case scenario,
最坏的情况是，
you crash,
你会崩溃，
and the system fails, and you could corrupt your data.
系统出现故障，你可能会损坏你的数据。
So we need latches to protect this thing.
所以我们需要 latch 来保护这个东西。
And so the technique we're going to use is called latch crabbing or latch coupling,
所以，我们将使用的技术称为 latch 抓取或 latch 耦合，
I think the textbook calls it latch coupling,
我想教科书把它叫做 latch 耦合，
I think the Wikipedia calls it latch latch coupling, right,
我认为维基百科称其为 latch 耦合，
but it's basically the protocol we're going to use to decide
但这基本上是我们要用来决定的协议，
as we traverse down our tree,
在向下遍历树时，
what latches we want to take
我们想要获取什么 latch ，
and then when can we release the latches up above us.
然后什么时候释放我们上面的 latch 。
Because again, the easiest way to protect this entire data structure is
因为再次，保护整个数据结构的最简单方法是，
put a giant latch on top, the whole thing,
在顶部放一个巨大的 latch ，
and then everyone has to get gatekeep through,
然后每个人都必须通过[门禁]，
but then that becomes a bottleneck.
但是随后，这就成为了一个瓶颈。
So we want to be more clever
所以我们想变得更聪明，
and selectively release our latches as we go down,
有选择地释放我们的 latch ，
when we know it's okay.
当我们知道可以的时候。
So the basic protocol is,
所以基本的协议是，
in order for me to go into B+ tree,
为了进入 B+ 树，
you always set to latch the root,
你总是给 root 设置 latch ，
but, but once I'm in my my root
但是，一旦我在我的 root 上，
and I I figure out whether I want to go left and right
我找出我想要向左或向右，
and then I acquire the latch of my child,
然后我拿到子节点的 latch ，
that I'm going to go down from the current parent I'm at
我要向下的当前所在的父节点，
and then once I'm know I'm okay
然后一旦我知道我可以了，
and I'm able to go there,
我可以去那里，
I can release my parent latch for that current node I'm at
我可以释放我当前所在节点的父节点的 latch ，
if if I know it's safe.
如果我知道它是安全的。
And the definition of safe is going to be that,
安全的定义将是，
we know that based on the operation we're trying to do, insert or delete,
基于我们试图执行的操作，插入或删除，
if it's an insert,
如果它是插入，
we know that the child isn't full
我们知道子节点没有填满，
and therefore if I, if I had to do a split,
因此，如果我必须拆分，
sorry, when I insert my key,
抱歉，当我插入我的键时，
it's not going to cause to do a split at that child node,
它不会导致在那个子节点进行拆分，
which may get propagated up to the parent.
这可能会传播到父节点。
If I'm going to do a delete,
如果我要执行删除，
if I know that it's more than half full,
如果我知道它已经半满，
then again, if I remove a key,
那么，如果我删除一个键，
I know I'm not going to do a merge,
我知道我不会执行合并，
which again, we propagate things up to my parent node here, right.
我们将事情向上传播到我的父节点。
So again, the basic protocol is,
所以，基本的协议是，
I started the root traverse down,
我从 root 开始，向下遍历，
acquire read latches on every child,
获取每个子节点的读 latch ，
as I'm going down,
随着我向下，
because again, I'm doing a read operation,
因为我是在做读操作，
I'm not doing updates,
我不是在做更新，
and then I just unlatch my parent,
然后我只是 unlatch 父节点，
for doing insert or delete,
对于执行插入或删除，
I start at root,
我从 root 开始，
taking write latches as I go down
获取写 latch ，随着我向下，
and then once I have my child,
然后一旦我有我的子节点，
know that I'm going to move to in write mode,
知道我将进入写模式，
then I go check to see whether it's safe
然后我去检查它是否安全，
and if it is safe
如果它是安全的，
and I can go release any latches I have up above me.
我可以去释放任何我上面的 latch 。
So let's go back to our example here.
所以让我们回到这里的例子。
So I want to find key 38,
所以我想查找键 38 ，
I start the root,
我从 root 开始，
take the root in, in root node in write latch mode,
把 root 节点放入写 latch 模式，
I get down to,
我向下，
sorry, then I acquire the the read latch on B,
抱歉，然后我获取 B 上的读 latch ，
then I move down
然后我向下移动，
and at this point here,
在这里，
it's safe for me to release the latch on, on A,
我可以安全地释放 A 上的 latch ，
because again, it's doing a read operation,
因为它执行读操作，
I've already arrived at B,
我已经到达了 B ，
where I need to go,
我需要去的地方，
so I'm going to go there,
所以我要去那里，
so I can go ahead and release the latch on B,
这样我就可以继续，释放 B 上的 latch ，
get the latch, read latch on D,
获取 D 上的读 latch ，
same thing, it's safe for me to release the latch on B,
同样的事情，对我来说，释放 B 上的 latch 是安全的，
so I'll go ahead and do that
所以我会继续这样做，
and I get down to H and so forth
我下到 H ，依此类推，
and I finally get the key I'm looking for,
我最终拿到了我要找的键，
and I'm done.
我就完成了。
Alright, it's delete 38 now.
好的，现在是删除 38 。
Again, started the root,
再次，从 root 开始，
I get the root in, in root latch, the root node in write mode latch,
我把 root 节点放入写 latch 模式，
I get a write latch on B, move down here,
我获取 B 的写 latch ，向下移动到这里，
and again, at this point here,
再次，在这一点上，
if I, if I do,
如果我做，
I don't know what's going to happen below me in the tree, below B
我不知道在我下面的树中，在 B 下面会发生什么，
and because if I know if I have to delete a key from the node I'm currently at, at B,
因为如果我知道必须从当前所在的节点删除一个键，在 B 上面，
I'm gonna have to do a merge,
我将不得不进行合并，
so therefore I can't release the latch on my parent A,
所以，我不能释放我父节点 A 上的 latch ，
because I, I may have to go make changes to A of above,
因为我可能不得不去更改上面的 A ，
so I'm going to hold the write latch on on on B and A,
所以我将持有 B 和 A 的写 latch ，
get down to D,
下到 D ，
now at D, I see that,
现在在 D 上，我看到，
no matter what happens to me below in the tree,
无论我在树的下面发生了什么，
if I had to remove a key from D,
如果我必须从 D 中删除一个键，
D, it's not going to do do do a merge,
D ，它将不会进行合并，
and therefore, it's not going to make any changes up above it,
所以，它不会在它上面做任何改变，
so it's safe for me to go ahead and release the latches on A and B.
所以，我可以安全地释放 A 和 B 上的 latch 。
Does the order matter?
顺序重要吗？
Sorry, question.
抱歉，请提问。
Whatever you're at now, whatever the,
不管你现在在什么上面，
so if I, if I'm at B,
所以如果我在 B 上面，
I get the and I need to go to D,
我需要去 D 上面，
so I get, I get it in write, I get the latch in write mode,
我将 latch 设置为写模式，
and then now I have write mode,
现在我有了写模式，
then I check, am I safe.
然后我检查一下，我安全吗。
This question is,
这个问题是，
is is it being half full, the only check to see whether it's safe
半满是是看它是否安全唯一的检查吗，
and what else, what else would cause a merge in case of a delete.
还有什么会导致合并，在删除的情况下。
That's the thing we only care about, like splits emerges,
这是我们唯一关心的事情，拆分、合并，
we're trying to make sure that we don't screw ourselves with that.
我们努力确保我们不会把自己搞砸。
All right, so,
好的，所以，
so at this one here at D,
所以在 D 这个位置上，
we had to release the latches on A and B,
我们必须释放 A 和 B 上的 latch ，
because, again, D is safe.
因为， D 是安全的。
Does the order in which we release those latches matter?
我们释放这些 latch 的顺序重要吗？
He says it makes more sense going from the bottom to the top
他说，从底部到顶部这样做更有意义，
by releasing B, followed by A, why?
先释放 B ，再释放 A ，为什么？
So if I release B and someone waiting for A.
所以如果我释放 B ，有人在等待 A 。
Yes.
是的。
So, he says, if you release B, then it does,
所以，他说，如果你释放 B ，然后它，
sorry, the other thread, waiting for B or A, sorry.
抱歉，另一个线程，等待 B 或 A ，抱歉。
Yeah, has on the same [path].
是的，在同一[路径]上。
A latch, but yes, yeah, okay.
一个 latch ，是的，是的，好的。
But if I release it on B,
但是如果我在 B 上释放它，
it still waiting for A.
它仍在等待 A 。
Also, too, what if I have a thread that's waiting for A,
同样，如果我有一个线程正在等待 A ，
but I want to go down this side of the tree,
但我想从树的这一边下来怎么办，
but I release B,
但我会释放 B ，
it's still blocked.
它还是阻塞的。
So from a correctness reason,
所以从正确的理由来看，
from a correctness standpoint,
从正确的角度来看，
it doesn't actually matter.
这实际上并不重要。
Like the system, the the data structure will still be correct,
就像系统，数据结构都是正确的，
whether you go from the bottom to the top, top of the bottom.
无论你从底部到顶部，从底部的顶部。
For performance reasons,
出于性能原因，
we want to go top down,
我们想要自上而下，
because we want to release,
因为我们想要释放，
like you way to think about it is
比如你想象它是，
the latch is protecting everything below it,
latch 是在保护它下面的一切，
so if I hold a write latch on the root,
所以，如果我在 root 上持有写 latch ，
I'm protecting the entire data structure in write mode, right.
我就是在以写模式保护整个数据结构。
Now, there may be a bunch of read threads and other threads doing stuff over here,
现在，这里可能有一堆读线程和其他线程在做一些事情，
but that's okay, because it would have,
但这没有关系，因为它会这样，
if their modifications would have caused us to do a split or merge,
如果他们的修改会导致我们进行拆分或合并，
then up the entire to the root,
然后向上整个到 root ，
they would have to still hold the write latch on this.
他们仍然必须在这上面持有写 latch 。
So again, the main takeaway is that,
所以，主要的结论是，
we want to release latches as soon as possible,
我们希望尽快释放 latch ，
so, and we want to release latches
所以，我们希望释放 latch ，
that will have the most,
它会最大地，
that would free up the most, most of our workers in our data structure,
释放我们数据结构中的最大多数的 worker ，
so we always want to release from the top going down.
所以我们总是希望从上到下释放。
All right, so then we get down here
好的，然后我们下到这里，
and we get the write latch on H,
我们得到 H 上的写 latch ，
go ahead and do our delete and we're done.
继续，做我们的删除，我们就完成了。
All right, so let's look at another example,
好的，让我们来看另一个例子，
I'm going to insert 45,
我将插入 45 ，
same idea,
相同的想法，
I get the write latch on the root, on A
我获得 root 上的写 latch ，在 A 上面，
go down to B,
向下到 B ，
at this point here,
在这一点上，
I know that if, if,
我知道如果，
whatever is below me in the tree,
树上我下面的任何东西，
if it has to do a split,
如果它必须拆分，
I have room in B to accommodate another key,
我在 B 中有空间容纳另一个键，
so it's okay for me to go release the latch on A,
所以我可以释放 A 上面的 latch ，
get down here on D,
下到这里的 D ，
now, D is completely full,
现在，D 完全满了，
I don't know what's below me in the tree,
我不知道在树上我下面是什么，
because I haven't gone there yet,
因为我还没有去过那里，
so this point here, it's not safe to release,
所以这一点上，释放是不安全的，
to release the latch on D
释放 D 上的 latch ，
until I go down,
直到我向下，
and now I can see that,
现在我可以看到，
inserting to I, would not cause a split on node I,
插入到 I ，不会在节点 I 上引起拆分，
so I can go ahead and release the latches on B and D
所以我可以继续，释放 B 和 D 上的 latch ，
going top down,
从上到下，
and I can insert my key.
我可以插入我的键。
All right, let's look one where there is a split, right.
好的，让我们看一个有拆分的。
For simplicity, we we could ignore sibling pointers,
为了简单起见，我们可以忽略兄弟指针，
so I'm doing insert 25, B is safe,
所以我做的是插入 25 ， B 是安全的，
I'm going to release the latch on A,
我要释放 A 上的 latch ，
I get down to C, C is safe,
我要下到 C ， C 是安全的，
release the latch on B,
释放 B 上的 latch ，
then I get down to F, F is not safe,
然后我下到 F ， F 不是安全的，
so I can't release the latch on, on C,
所以我不能释放 C 上的 latch ，
and now I need to do a split
现在我需要进行拆分，
and that split's going to cause me to insert a new entry up into node C,
这个拆分将导致我在节点 C 中插入一个新条目，
so I'll go ahead and do that,
所以我会继续，
add my new, add my new node J,
添加我的新节点 J ，
I'm out of space because this PowerPoint,
我没有空间了，因为这个幻灯片，
again, we're ignoring sibling pointers for now,
再次，我们现在忽略兄弟指针，
go ahead and now do the update to the C,
继续，现在更新 C ，
could now include this pointer,
现在可以包括这个指针，
and then once, once I apply all these changes,
然后，一旦我应用了所有这些更改，
then I release the latches going top down.
然后我释放从上到下的 latch 。
So I've already given this answer before,
我之前已经给出了这个答案，
but what was the very first thing I did for all these scenarios,
但是对于所有这些场景，我做的第一件事是什么，
when I want to do updates and inserts and deletes,
当我想要进行更新、插入和删除时，
what's the very first thing you have to do?
你必须做的第一件事是什么？
Get a latch on the, yeah, get a latch on the root node, right.
获取 root 节点的 latch 。
And like, yeah, that's correct,
是的，没错，
but this is a bottleneck now,
但这现在是一个瓶颈，
because it basically becomes almost a single threaded data structure,
因为它基本上一个单线程数据结构，
that everybody has to go into the system,
几乎每个都必须进入系统，
sorry, going to our data structure,
抱歉，进入我们的数据结构，
the first thing get to do is is,
首先要做的是，
acquire the latch in write mode, in the root,
获取 root 节点上写模式的 latch ，
if you're doing reads, that's not gonna be compatible,
如果你做读取，它是不兼容的，
so it'll block all the readers too.
所以它也会阻塞所有读取者。
Again, it's correct,
再次，它是正确的，
but for my performance reasons,
但是出于性能的原因，
it's, it's not ideal.
它不是很理想。
And so the, the common technique everyone uses is,
所以大家常用的技术就是，
this optimistic latching scheme I'll talk about now,
我现在要谈的这个乐观的 latch 方案，
I don't think the algorithm has a name,
我不认为这个算法有名字，
it's from this paper,
它来自这篇论文，
from, I think it's from, from the 70s,
来自于 70 年代，
is there date on that,
上面有日期吗，
7, it says 77, yeah,
7 ，它显示 77 ，是的，
from these guys at IBM Bayer and Schkolnick,
来自两个 IBM 的人， Bayer 和 Schkolnick ，
sometimes it's called the Bayer-Schkolnick algorithm,
有时它被称为 Bayer-Schkolnick 算法，
which is kind of cumbersome to say,
这说起来有点麻烦，
but, it's based on this observation,
但是，它基于这种观察，
that you know that most of your threads, most of your workers,
你的大多数线程和你的大多数 worker ，
their operations are, are are not going to cause a split or merge into to your, your B+ tree nodes,
他们的操作不会导致你的 B+ 树节点的拆分或合并，
again, my example here,
同样，我在这里的例子中，
I'm showing nodes with two keys in it,
我展示了带有两个键的节点，
because that's a fit of the PowerPoint,
因为这是适合幻灯片的，
but in a real system,
但在实际系统中，
you know the the size of a node is going to be the page size to your database,
节点的大小将是数据库的页面大小，
so like 8 kilobytes, 16 kilobytes
比如 8 千字节， 16 千字节，
and you can store a lot of keys,
你可以存储很多键，
the most of the times you do a bunch of inserts
大多数情况下，你做一堆插入，
and that's not not going cause any, any splits,
这不会导致任何拆分，
and likewise for deletes.
对于删除也是如此。
So if you assume that splits merges will be rare,
所以，如果你假设拆分合并是罕见的，
then instead of taking write latches all the way down,
那么，不是一直向下持有写 latch ，
even if you're doing the the the latch, the latch coupling scheme,
即使你使用 latch 耦合方案，
you're going to take read latches -} all the way down,
你要一直向下持有读 latch ，
until you get to a leaf node, right above the leaf node,
直到到达叶子节点，叶子节点的正上方，
and then now you check to see
然后现在检查，
whether that assumption that you're not going to do a split or merge is correct,
不会进行拆分或合并的假设是否正确，
and if it is,
如果是这样，
then you go ahead and acquire the leaf node in write mode
那么你继续，获取叶子节点为写模式，
and, and then do your change,
然后进行更改，
but if you're wrong,
但是如果你错了，
you just restart and then do the pessimistic approach,
你只需重新开始，然后采取悲观的方法，
you just taking write latches all the way down.
你一直向下持有写 latch 。
So this would be a common theme, you see,
所以，这将是一个共同的主题，
not just in databases and a bunch of different systems in general,
不仅是在数据库，而且在一系列不同的系统中，
this is sort of optimistic scheme,
这是一种乐观的方案，
where you assume that there're not going to be any issues, not any problems,
你假设不会有任何问题，
and you do the sort of the fast way
你会以一种快速的方式，
of, of, of making some change or doing something in your system,
在你的系统中做出一些改变或做一些事情，
and then if you're wrong,
然后，如果你错了，
you just roll it back and take care of it.
你就把它倒回去，然后处理它。
Intel actually had this, it was called TSX,
Intel 有这个，它被称为 TSX ，
we actually had this in the, in the CPU itself,
我们在 CPU 本身就有这个，
I think,
我想，
it was a bug and I think they turned it off,
这是一个 bug ，我想他们把它关掉了，
it might have got turned back on,
它可能重新打开，
but it was like this optimistic memory stuff,
但它就像这种乐观内存的东西，
where you could have a critical section,
你可以有一个临界区，
where you would assume you're not going to have any conflicts in some critical section
假设你不会在某个临界区有任何冲突，
and then when you went to go apply the change,
然后当你去应用更改时，
then you just just check
然后你只需检查，
to see whether that, that that, that assumption was correct
查看那个假设是否正确，
and if not, it would roll you back automatically.
如果不正确，它会自动回退。
But again, we'll see this,
但是同样，我们会看到这个，
when we do talk about [] for transactions,
当我们讨论[]事务时，
this is a very common technique,
这是一种非常常见的技术，
you do the fast thing,
你做快速的事情，
because that most of the times there won't be any issues
因为大多数时候不会有任何问题，
and if you're wrong,
如果你错了，
then you have to roll back and try again.
那么你必须回滚并再次尝试。
All right, so with this better latching scheme,
好的，所以，有了这个更好的 latch 方案，
for, for doing lookup and finds, that's the same as before,
对于查找，这与以前是相同的，
for inserts and deletes,
对于插入和删除，
again, we take we, we basically do the search,
我们使用，我们基本上做搜索，
taking write latches, sorry, read latches all the way down
持有写 latch ，抱歉，读 latch 一直向下，
until we're one level above the the leaf node,
直到我们位于叶子节点的上一级别，
I mean, we know where we're in the, in the, in the, the data structure,
我的意思是，我们知道我们在数据结构中的位置，
because, you know, we can keep track of how many levels down we are
因为，我们可以跟踪我们向下的级别，
either in the page or a simple counter would work too.
不论是在页面中或者一个简单的计数器也可以。
You go acquire the the level right above the leaf node,
你可以获取叶子节点正上方的级别，
you acquire the leaf node in in write mode,
你在写模式下获取叶子节点，
then you check to see whether it's safe,
然后你检查它是否安全，
if it is safe,
如果它是安全的，
then you release all your read latches that you took from before,
然后你释放你以前拿到的所有读 latch ，
apply your change and you're done,
应用你的更改，你就完成了，
if you're wrong,
如果你错了，
then you just release all your latches
那么你只要释放你所有的 latch ，
and go back and take write latches all the way down.
然后回去持有写 latch 一直向下。
You could take, you know, do the optimistic scheme again,
你可以再使用乐观的方案，
because you assume next time you come back around,
因为你假设下次你回来的时候，
things will be safe,
一切都会安全的，
it depends on the implementation.
这取决于实现。
And so this works really well in low contention environments,
所以，这在争用较少的环境中工作得非常好，
because you obviously assume there won't be any conflicts
因为你显然认为不会有任何冲突，
and most of the time you're correct,
而且大多数情况下你是正确的，
and so things run faster.
所以，事情运行得更快。
So let's go back, for example before,
所以让我们回到前面的例子，
let's delete key 38,
让我们删除键 38 ，
again, instead of taking the root node in, in, in a write latch mode,
不是以写 latch 模式持有根节点，
taking a read mode, keep going down,
持有读模式，继续向下，
so I get down to D,
所以我下到了 D ，
now D recognizes that it's one level above the leaf node,
现在 D 意识到它比叶子节点高一级，
so I want to delete key 38 from, from node H,
所以我想从节点 H 中删除键 38 ，
so I take the H into write mode,
所以我将 H 放入写模式，
check to see it's safe,
检查它是否安全，
it is, I can go delete it,
它是的，我可以删除它，
and I know I'm not going to do any,
我知道我不会做任何，
I'm not going to do any merges, right.
我不会做任何合并。
So again, best case scenario,
所以，再次，最好的情况是，
I I traversed the data structure
我遍历数据结构，
almost as if I was doing a read,
几乎就像我在做读取，
and therefore, I can have a maximum amount of parallelism,
所以，我可以有最大的并行度，
but only at the bottom,
但只有在底部，
do I check to see whether that assumption was correct.
我才会检查这个假设是否正确。
See how to do insert, insert 25,
看看如何做插入 25 ，
again, take the root in in read mode,
再次，把 root 放入读模式，
take B in read mode,
把 B 放入读模式，
do the latch coupling, as I release latches go down,
当我释放 latch 向下时，做 latch 耦合，
now I get down here into F,
现在我在这里进入 F ，
in case of F,
在 F 的情况下，
because we're trying to do an insert,
因为我们要做插入，
F doesn't have any more room, so it's not safe,
F 没有更多的空间，所以它是不安全的，
so we're going have to restart the whole operation
所以，我们必须重新启动整个操作，
and then just take write latches on the way down.
然后在下降的过程中持有写 latch 。
Neat trick, right?
巧妙的方法，对吧？
Okay.
好的。
So, in all these examples I've shown so far,
所以，在我到目前为止展示的所有这些例子中，
we were only going in one direction,
我们只朝一个方向走，
we were only going top to the bottom,
我们只是从上到下，
as I said, there weren't any deadlocks,
就像我说的，这里没有任何死锁，
because nobody, you know, everyone's going to the top,
因为每个人都会到顶部，
they're always starting the same point and they're going down,
它们总是从同一个点开始，然后向下，
there's no, you know, as I said last class,
这里没有，就像我上一节课说的，
there's no pointers to your parent,
没有指向你父节点的指针，
you can't go back up
你不能向上回去，
and because that's where you could have conflicts.
因为那样可能会发生冲突。
Again, because we're a B+ tree,
再次，因为我们是 B+ 树，
we could have sibling pointers.
我们可以有兄弟指针。
And now we have a challenge,
现在我们有一个挑战，
where we could have one thread going one way
我们可以让一个线程走一条路，
and another thread going another way,
另一个线程走另一条路，
and they both hold latches for what the other person wants, what the other thread wants, right.
它们都持有用于另一个线程想要的东西的 latch 。
So now we've got to deal with that scenario,
所以现在我们要处理那个场景，
the original B+ tree paper, this wasn't an issue,
原始的 B+ 树论文，这不是一个问题，
but the B-link stuff that came from CMU,
但是来自 CMU 的 B-Link 的东西，
that's where they added sibling pointers,
这就是他们添加兄弟指针的地方，
and that's where you can have deadlocks.
这就是你可能会有死锁的地方。
So let's look at a simple example here.
让我们来看一个简单的例子。
So I want thread 1,
所以我想要线程 1 ，
they want to find all keys less than 4,
他们想要找到所有小于 4 的键，
so I'm going to get the root in read mode
所以我将在读模式中获取 root ，
and then get the C in read mode
然后在读模式中获取 C ，
and then let's say,
然后我们假设，
and then once the scan, scan across,
然后一旦扫描完毕，
so it's going to follow the sibling pointers,
所以，它将跟随兄弟指针，
so just like before, I hold,
所以，就像以前一样，我持有，
whatever node I'm at now,
无论我在哪个节点，
I hold that in the current latch mode, I have it,
我持有它在当前我有的 latch 模式下，
and then I, then try to acquire the latch to where I want to go to,
然后试着获取我想去的地方的 latch ，
so in this case here,
所以，在这种情况下，
again to C, go from C to B,
再次，从 C 到 B ，
so I hold the latch on C,
所以我持有 C 上的 latch ，
get the latch on B,
获取 B 上的 latch ，
move over here and then I can release the latch on C
移动到这里，然后我可以释放 C 上的 latch ，
and then do whatever it is that I need to do, right.
然后做任何我需要做的事情。
So the protocol is basically the same thing,
所以协议基本上是一样的，
even though we're now moving horizontally instead of vertically.
尽管我们现在是水平移动而不是垂直移动。
Yes.
是的。
We'll get that in a second, yes,
我们马上就到那里，是的，
same schedule, yes.
相同的调度，是的。
So again, the read modes are [] commutative,
所以，读模式是可交换的，
so I can have two threads I'm going to read at the same time,
所以我可以有两个线程在同一时间读取，
I, first I goes down, or thread goes down, goes down to C,
首先，线程往下到 C ，
second, thread goes down to B
第二，线程下到 B ，
and they want to go across each other,
它们想要彼此交叉，
and in this case here,
在这种情况下，
the the two latches they're holding are commutative,
它们拿着的两个 latch 是可交换的，
so therefore, they can both do whatever they need to do, right.
所以，它们都可以做任何它们需要做的事情。
That's fine.
那是好的。
So let's now do,
所以我们现在做，
when we have a,
当我们有一个，
one of them wants to do a write, one wants to do a read.
其中一个想要写入，一个想要读取。
So T1 wants to delete the key 4
所以 T1 想要删除键 4 ，
and T2 wants to find all keys greater than 1.
T2 想要找到所有大于 1 的键。
So they both start at the same time
所以，它们同时启动，
and assume we're doing the optimistic lock coupling,
假设我们进行乐观锁耦合，
I just talked about latch coupling,
我刚才说的是 latch 耦合，
where they started the root, both, both in, in read mode, right,
它们都以读模式从 root 开始，
thread 2 goes down, takes B into read mode,
线程 2 向下，把 B 带入读模式，
thread C goes down and takes, takes,
线程 C 向下，
sorry, thread 1 goes down, takes node C in write mode,
抱歉，线程 1 向下，把 C 放入写模式，
and that's the key that it wants to delete, right.
这是它想要删除的键。
But now thread 2, scanning across leaf nodes
但是现在线程 2 在叶子节点上扫描，
and it wants to acquire the latch C in read mode,
它想要在读模式下获取 C 的 latch ，
but it can't,
但它不能，
because T1 holds that in write mode,
因为 T1 在写模式下持有它，
so we have to decide what we want to do here, right.
所以我们必须决定我们想要在这里做什么。
And T2 doesn't know anything about T1,
T2 对 T1 一无所知，
because I said, there's no centralized data structure that says,
因为我说过，没有集中化的数据结构来说明，
here's the threads that are running,
这是正在运行的线程，
here's, you know, here's what they're doing,
这是他们正在做的，
all that sees, all it knows is that,
它所知道的是，
there's a latch on this other node that I want to go to,
在我想要访问的另一个节点上有一个 latch ，
and it's currently in write mode
它目前处于写模式，
and that's not compatible with the mode I want to put it in,
与我想要设置的模式不兼容，
so you have to do something.
所以你必须做些什么。
So what can T2 do here?
那么 T2 能在这里做些什么？
The wait, that one option, what else?
等待，那是一个选项，还有什么？
What's that?
那是什么？
Kill Ourself, are you reading the slides, okay,
杀死自己，你在看幻灯片吗，好的，
what's the third option?
第三种选择是什么？
and [go street] on the other thread and try to kill, kill it
去另一个线程，试图杀死它，
and take the latch from it.
从它上面取下 latch 。
So what do you think is a good idea here?
那么，你认为在这里什么是一个好主意？
What's that, says wait, for how long?
是什么，等待，等待多久？
Yeah, forever,
好的，永远，
how long,
多久，
but how do you know.
但你怎么知道。
But that just waiting, right,
但那只是等待，
it just spinning until the latch is available, but like,,
它只是旋转，直到 latch 可用，就像，
how to say this?
这话怎么说呢？
Do you know what T T1 is, you know what T1 is doing,
你知道 T1 在做什么吗，
no, we don't know anything, right.
不，我们什么都不知道。
Do you,
你知道吗，
well, you know it's in right mode,
你知道它是在写模式，
but how long is it going to take?
但它将需要多长时间？
How?
怎么做?
Which one,
哪个，
like, do you kill yourself from your schedule,
比如，从你的调度中杀死自己，
do you kill the other guy in your schedule,
从你的调度中杀死其他线程，
what do you want to do,
你想做什么，
she says kill ourself, fantastic, right,
她说关掉杀死自己，太棒了，
how do you do that,
你怎么做，
what's that?
是什么？
What do you mean,
你是什么意思，
keep a log everything you done in the past.
把你过去做的每一件事都记下来。
Yeah, that sounds expensive,
是的，听起来很昂贵，
what is a normal amount of time?
正常的时间是多少？
He says, wait for the average time for a write to happen.
他说，等待写入发生的平均时间。
But like you don't say,
但是你没有，
in my simple example here,
在我这个简单的例子中，
because the [] and PowerPoint,
因为[]和幻灯片，
there's two nodes in the leaf, right,
这里有两个叶子节点，
what if there was a bunch of leaf nodes all over here,
如果这里有很多叶子节点一直到这里，
I got to hold all these guys in everything in write mode, right,
我得让所有的人都保持在写模式，
because I want my change to happen atomically,
因为我希望我的更改自动发生，
so I don't know whether this other thread keep going in the other direction,
所以我不知道其他线程是否继续朝着相反的方向前进，
I don't like what is a normal time, you don't know.
我不喜欢什么是正常时间，你不知道。
He says give up your write lock and let the other guy read,
他说放弃你的写锁，让另一个线程来读，
but how do you know,
但你怎么知道，
how do you know they're waiting for you,
你怎么知道它们在等你，
like, if you're T1,
比如，如果你是 T1 ，
how do you know somebody else is trying to get your latch.
你怎么知道其他线程想获取你的 latch 。
Yes.
是的。
Bingo, there you go, excellent.
是的，就是这样，太棒了。
So you should kill yourself, right, right,
所以你应该杀死自己，
so killing other thread is hard,
杀死其他线程是很困难的，
because how would you implement that,
因为你如何实现它，
can you send interrupt, interrupt [],
你能发送中断[]吗，
that's expensive, right, that's a syscall,
那很昂贵，那是一个系统调用，
is there like a flag,
有没有一个标志，
you say, should I kill myself,
你会说，我应该杀死自己吗，
and you have to check that every so often,
你必须每隔一段时间检查一次，
how would that work,
这怎么工作，
checking some other memory location, right,
检查其他内存位置，
and, and what do you get,
然后，你得到了什么，
you get the,
你得到，
you know, you don't know how much work the other thread, the other thread is done
你不知道另一个线程做了多少工作，
and therefore you don't know whether him aborting and rolling back is
你不知道他是否会中止和回退，
was way more expensive than than than you abort yourself,
这比你自己中止代价要高得多，
you know nothing at this point, right.
在这一点上你什么都不知道。
So the best thing to do is just kill yourself,
所以最好的办法就是杀死自己，
and then you maybe you also could wait a little bit in the beginning
然后也许你也可以在开始的时候等待一段时间，
and then give up right away,
然后立即放弃，
depending on what you know you need to do, right.
取决于你需要做什么。
And so this is the simplest thing to do,
所以这是最简单的事情，
and it turns out to be the best thing to do
事实证明，这是最好的事情，
in most scenarios, all scenarios,
在大多数情况下，所有情况下，
because again, you don't know anything about the thread,
因为再次，你对线程一无所知，
you can't communicate with the other thread, because that's expensive,
你不能与另一个线程通信，因为这很昂贵，
and you're just better off aborting and starting over again.
你最好放弃，然后重新开始。
Yes.
是的。
So his statement is,
所以他的说法是，
you would have to wait also too or kill itself too,
你也必须等待或杀死自己，
like when you're doing the traversal of the tree going top down,
当你在做树的自上而下的遍历时，
if I try to acquire a latch on somebody else on the next node,
如果我试图获取下一个节点上的 latch ，
but that's already being held, what I do,
但它已经被持有了，我应该做什么，
it's the same scenario here,
这里是同样的情况，
that same scenario, but in that case, you're not,
同样的情况，但在这种情况下，你不是，
you won't deadlock though, right.
你不会死锁。
The problem is,
问题是，
like again, if if T2 wants to get the latch on on,
如果 T2 想要获取 latch ，
T1 wants to get the latch on B,
T1 想要获取 B 的 latch ，
and T2 wants to latch on C,
T2 想要获取 C 的 latch ，
that's a deadlock,
这是一个死锁，
you don't know, that it's a deadlock or just contention acquiring some latch, right,
你不知道，这是一个死锁或者只是争抢了一些 latch ，
so the best thing to do is immediately give up.
所以最好的办法就是立即放弃。
And that means you could have a scenario,
这意味着你可能会有这样一种情况，
where you hold the latch and I hold the latch
你持有 latch ，我持有 latch ，
and one of us should only give up,
我们中的只有一个人应该放弃，
but we end up both giving up and killing ourselves, right.
但我们最终既放弃又杀死自己。
But again, the cost of maintaining metadata about who's waiting for what in what way,
但是，维护关于谁在以何种方式等待什么的元数据的成本，
that's more expensive to do in the regular case where you assume there isn't contention.
在假设没有争用的常规情况下要更昂贵。
Yeah, so it was this one here, right,
是的，所以就是这个，
so they're both doing reads,
所以它们都在读取，
but assume they're both doing writes, right,
但假设他们都在写入，
I need, I need to update all keys greater than 1 or something
我需要更新所有的大于 1 的键，
he needs to update keys less than 4, right,
他需要更新小于 4 的键，
I'm going this way, he's gone that way,
我要往这边走，他要往那边走，
we have that's a deadlock.
我们有一个死锁。
Think in terms of latches,
就 latch 而言，
I'm trying to acquire latch on this direction,
我试图在这个方向上获取 latch ，
trying to that direction
试图在那个方向上获取 latch ，
and we're deadlocked.
我们死锁了。
Your question is how to prevent both of them killing themselves.
你的问题是如何防止他们两个都杀死自己。
So, like, you can't,
所以，你不能，
because I don't know, I don't know you exist,
因为我不知道你的存在，
I don't know what you're doing, right,
我不知道你做了什么，
yeah, and you know, if you just think of computers in general,
如果你只考虑一般的计算机，
like it's very unlikely that,
比如，不太可能，
you and I gonna be exact lockstep in our threads
你和我在我们的线程步调一致，
and the exact same like number of cycles,
以及完全相同的周期数量，
we're both going to try to acquire a latch together that then would deadlock,
我们都会试图获得一个 latch ，然后就会死锁，
we go kill each other,
我们要杀死对方，
it's, it's a, it's a race condition,
这是一种竞态条件，
but it's, it's, it's rare,
但它是罕见的，
but you can't prevent it,
但你无法预防它，
because the cost of preventing it is so expensive.
因为预防它的成本太高了。
The statement is,
这种说法是，
from a philosophical standpoint,
从哲学的角度来看，
it would be more efficient to kill the other one,
杀死另一个会更有效率，
would that be better?
这会更好吗？
It's not really philosophical question,
这不是一个哲学问题，
it's just like, straight up, is it better,
它是，直截了当地，是不是更好，
like you take their wallet, whatever you like.
比如，你拿走他们的钱包，无论你喜欢的什么。
Like, this is a toy example,
这是一个玩具例子，
where like it's only one node,
它只有一个节点，
like if you think about,
如果你想一想，
I don't know what the, I don't know what work you've done,
我不知道你做了什么，
I don't, you don't know what I've done,
你不知道我做了什么，
if we can sort of keep track of that,
如果我们能追踪到这个，
then we may maybe decide,
那么我们可能会决定，
okay, well you hold five latches, I hold one,
好的，你持有五个 latch ，我持有一个，
it's better to kill me,
最好杀死我，
because you did, you had to wait a bunch of time to get those five latches,
因为你需要等好长时间才能拿到那五个 latch ，
so that's sort of a high level, what we'll do when we do transactions,
这是高级别的，当我们在做事务时，
they'll figure out who who gets priority or others
他们会确定谁获得优先权，
based on how much work they've done so far,
根据到目前为止完成的工作量，
at this lowest level,
在这个最低级别，
the latches are meant to be, so like fine-grainained and short,
latch 应该是细粒度和小的，
it's better just to kill yourself.
最好杀死自己。
All right.
好的。
It is possible,
这是可能的，
so the question is,
所以问题是，
could you basically have, could you starve a thread,
你能不能饿着一个线程，
is the term you want to use,
你是想用这个词吗，
could you starve a thread,
你能饿着一个线程，
because every single time you try to get something,
因为每一次你试图得到某样东西的时候，
it, it can't,
它都不能，
because someone else is in there,
因为里面有别的东西，
could you strave that, yes.
你能饿着它吗，是的。
So,
所以，
I think I have a slide on this.
我想我有一个关于这个的幻灯片。
Yeah, so,
是的，所以，
there's,
这里有，
I'll answer your question in a second,
我稍等一下回答你的问题，
like the the latches, the latches aren't gonna have anything to handle deadlocks for us,
latch 不会有任何东西来为我们处理死锁，
and it's not gonna have anything that can prevent starvation,
它也不会有任何防止饥饿的东西，
in the read write latches,
在读写 latch 中，
you can set priorities, like writers or readers
你可以给写入者或读取者设置优先级，
or you want to do FIFO or round robin scheduling,
或者你想要执行先进先出或循环调度，
but there's a high level construct scheduler inside,
但是在内部有一个高级别构造调度器，
oh, this, this, this worker is trying to run this query,
哦，这个 worker 试图运行这个查询，
trying to touch this data structure
试图访问这个数据结构，
and it keeps getting aborted,
但它一直被中止，
and I know it's getting aborted,
我知道它被中止，
because you know it's coming back with a retry message,
因为它会返回一个重试消息，
and therefore, maybe I wanna dechedule other workers running at the same time
所以，也许我想取消其他同时运行的 worker 的调度，
to make sure I always get through,
以确保我总是能通过，
that's had a way to basically handle that,
它有了一种处理这一问题的方法，
most systems basically let you know,
大多数系统都会，
let Jesus take the wheel, whatever the phrase you want to use
让耶稣掌舵吧，不管你想用什么短语，
and let it go at it, right,
让它去吧，
because eventually you should get through.
因为最终你会通过的。
Now, again, if I have a,
现在，如果我有一个，
you know, a thousand queries trying to run at the same time
一千个查询试图同时运行，
trying to all update the same key,
试图全部更新相同的键，
there's no magic scheduler that's gonna be able to handle that,
没有神奇的调度器能够处理这个，
everything's sort of get contention,
所有东西都会冲突，
end up being a single thread system.
最终变成了一个单线程系统。
So we want to optimize for the case,
所以，我们希望针对这种情况进行优化，
where we assume that the, we assume contention is gonna be low
我们假设冲突会很低，
and we want to sort of fast, fail fast, no wait policy,
我们希望很快失败，没有等待策略，
we just check, can I do it,
我们只是检查一下，我能做吗，
no, okay, let me retry again,
不，好的，让我再试一次，
because by the time, you know, when I go, go retry,
因为到那时，当我去重试的时候，
then then I'll be able to do what I need to do.
然后我就可以做我需要做的事情了。
His question is,
他的问题是，
while you're killing yourself,
当你杀死自己时，
so do you have to roll back any changes that you do,
你是否必须回滚所做的任何更改，
yes, in the code.
是的，在代码中。
So again, going back to the writer example here,
所以，再次，回到写入者的例子，
like if, if this thread that kills itself,
如果，如果这个线程杀死自己，
they had updated a bunch of things,
它们已经更新了一大堆东西，
is where you hold the write latches for those things, you updated,
你持有那些你更新的东西的 latch ，你更新了，
so you can go back and reverse those changes.
所以你就可以回去，撤销那些更改。
It's possible deadlock,
它可能会陷入死锁，
no, why would you get deadlock,
不，为什么你会陷入死锁，
if you already hold the latch,
如果你已经持有了 latch ，
why would you get deadlocked.
为什么你会陷入死锁。
So his question is,
所以他的问题是，
in what in what scenario do you need the backwards pointer in the sibling,
在什么情况下，你需要在兄弟节点中使用向后指针，
because, because it seems like it's causing problems for us, right.
因为这似乎给我们带来了麻烦。
Your query is this, right,
你的查询是这样的，
find keys less than 4, find keys is greater than 1.
查找小于 4 的键，查找大于 1 的键。
Same as you could start at 1 and go until you find 4,
就像你可以从 1 开始直到找到 4 ，
I have a billion keys, right,
我有十亿个键，
like and I.
而且我。
Yeah, that's just way more expensive,
是的，那只是昂贵了很多。
nobody does that, yeah.
没人会这么做，是的。
Yeah, so, so we didn't talk about skip list,
是的，我们没有讨论过跳表，
there was a actually,
这里有一个，
SingleStore, before it was SingleStore was MemSQL,
SingleStore ，在它是 SingleStore 之前是 MemSQL ，
they had these skip list and skip list only have,
他们有这些跳表，跳表只有，
because they it's a, it's a lot free data structure,
因为这是一个非常自由的数据结构，
which is a bad idea,
这是一个坏主意，
it's another, another topic,
这是另一个话题，
but like they, they had their skip list can only go in one direction,
但是他们的跳表只能往一个方向走，
so they had to do a bunch of tricks
所以他们不得不做一系列技巧，
of like having ways to jump into the data structure
比如有办法跳到数据结构中，
to, to like try to do reverse
尝试进行反向操作，
and then sort it and reverse,
然后对其进行排序和反向，
after you know, after, after you get it out,
在你把它拿出来之后，
it just makes life harder,
它只会让生活变得更难，
you can do it and avoids this deadlock issue.
你可以做这个，并避免这种死锁问题。
But it's still an example,
但它仍然是一个例子，
if you're traversing down,
如果你在向下遍历，
if I can't acquire the latch as I'm going down,
如果我在下落的时候拿不到 latch ，
it's not a deadlock,
那就不是死锁，
I still want to kill myself potentially usually.
我可能通常还是想杀死自己。
It still.
它仍然。
Yeah, so you still,
是的，所以你仍然，
you won't have deadlocks,
你不会有死锁，
if you do what you're proposing,
如果你按照你提议的去做，
but you still could have latch contention,
但你仍然可能会有 latch 争用，
where I can't get the latch,
我拿不到 latch ，
because somebody else holds it.
因为其他人也持有它。
And in that case, again,
在这种情况下，
usually you want to spin for a little bit and then kill yourself.
你会想要旋转一小段时间，然后杀死自己。
Yeah, you still want to kill yourself,
是的，你还是想杀死自己，
that sounds weird, but you know what I mean.
这听起来很奇怪，但你知道我的意思。
Yes.
是的。
. Yeah, so he's right,
是的，所以他是对的，
repeat what he said,
重复他所说的话，
so he basically said,
他基本上是说，
we know how much work we've done
我们知道我们做了多少工作，
and we did a lot of updates,
我们做了很多更新，
we know they were expensive to do,
我们知道，这样做的成本很高，
so could we have a heuristic that says,
那么，我们能不能有一个经验法说，
when we, we spin,
当我们旋转时，
determine how long we want to wait
我们想要等待多长时间，
based on how much work we've done,
可以根据我们做了多少工作来确定，
yes, you could do that,
是的，你可以这么做，
I don't think Postgres MySQL actually do that,
我不认为 Postgres MySQL 这么做了。
I might be wrong.
我可能是错的。
Would it be?
会是这样吗？
I mean, you can imagine,
我的意思是，你可以想象，
really simple heuristic,
非常简单的经验式方法，
a counter,
一个计数器，
I have a counter in my local address,
我在我的本地地址有一个计数器，
local memory for my worker,
我的 worker 的本地内存，
how many pages have I updated,
我更新了多少页面，
and for each page I updated,
对于我更新的每个页面，
wait, maybe an extra, you know, hundred microseconds something like that,
等待，也许是额外的几百微秒左右，
simple heuristics,
简单的经验法，
I don't know whether it actually makes sense or not to do it,
我不知道这样做是否真的有意义，
it's a [] out for all case and databases,
这对所有情况和数据库的一种[]，
it depends on the workload,
这取决于工作量，
depends on, you know, if everybody's updating a bunch of stuff,
这取决于，如果每个人都在更新一堆东西，
then maybe that's a bad idea,
那么也许这不是一个好主意，
but you have one thread, one worker,
但你有一个线程，一个 worker ，
that updates a little bit of things,
它更新了一些事情，
that maybe, yeah, that might make sense.
是的，这可能是有意义的。
But once if I try to update the same key,
但是一旦我尝试更新相同的键，
it gets, everything gets bogged, boggled down to a single threaded system,
所有东西都会陷入单线程系统，
that's the extreme case, though.
不过，这只是个极端的例子。
Yes.
是的。
How do you handle that,
你怎么处理那个，
they're dead, I mean, they restart.
他们都死了，我是说，他们会重新开始。
Yeah.
是的。
Yeah, so, so very clear,
是的，所以，非常清楚，
I say this in slide,
我用幻灯片来说明这一点，
the restart mechanism is transparent to the user.
重新开始机制对用户是透明的。
Yeah, I don't have a slides at this like.
是的，我没有这样的幻灯片。
Like I run a query
比如我运行一个查询，
and I have to traverse a B+ tree
我必须遍历一个 B+ 树，
and I and, and to go look at the primary key
然后我去查看主键，
and I can't get a latch as I'm going down,
当我向下移动时，我得不到 latch ，
I don't want to abort the query and go back to the user,
我不想中止查询，并返回到用户，
hey, look, I couldn't get a latch,
嘿，听着，我不能获得 latch ，
because they don't know what a latch is, right,
因为他们不知道什么是 latch ，
and then tell to restart, we do this transparently for you,
然后重新启动，我们为你透明地这样做，
so like, so like you submit one query,
所以你提交一个查询，
it may restart the the traverse one of the B+ tree multiple times,
它可能会多次重新开始遍历 B+ 树，
and, but you don't see that from the end user of the application,
但是从应用程序的最终用户那里看不到这一点，
we're doing it internally,
我们是在内部进行的，
it's just the query got a little bit slower, because of that.
只是因为这个，查询速度变慢了一点。
A lot of questions, sorry.
很多问题，抱歉。
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, absolutely,
是的，当然，
so the question is,
所以问题是，
is there a scenario,
有没有这样一种情况，
where someone has a write latch on the root
某个线程在 root 上有一个写 latch ，
and if you restart, you're going to come back and abort,
如果你重新启动，你会回来并取消，
absolutely, yes,
当然，是的，
it's unavoidable.
这是不可避免的。
I mean, the more keys you insert, the tree gets taller,
我的意思是，你插入的键越多，树就越高，
and therefore, the, the likelihood that someone's going to hold a write latch on the root goes down, right.
所以，有线程在 root 上持有写 latch 向下。
Going back to the stall stuff, too,
回到停滞的东西上，
it's not just how much work the other thread doing,
不仅仅是另一个线程做了多少工作，
like, like you have to sort of wait for,
比如，你必须对等待排序，
remember these, these data structures are backed by pages in the buffer pool that are on a disk,
记的，这些数据结构由位于磁盘上的缓冲池中的页面支持，
so even though I'm updating one key,
所以，即使我更新一个键，
the key I need to update might be not in memory
我需要更新的键可能不在内存中，
and I gotta go out the disk and get it,
我必须从磁盘中取出它，
so that's why,
这就是为什么，
and you don't want to stall,
你不想停滞，
you don't want to spin forever for a long time,
你不会想要永远旋转很长一段时间，
because you don't know,
因为你不知道，
like, you know, it has to go get a disk,
比如，它必须得到一个磁盘，
it's just a really slow disk
这只是一个非常慢的磁盘，
and that's going to be a long time
这将是一个很长的时间，
and you can be waiting for 100 milliseconds, 500 milliseconds.
你可以等待 100 毫秒， 500 毫秒。
So he said, oh, yeah, do the average time,
所以他说，哦，等待平均时间，
I mean, it depends on so many factors,
我的意思是，这取决于太多因素，
that would be impossible to track these things.
不可能跟踪这些东西。
Again, this is, again, this is why
再次，这就是为什么，
this is different than taking a regular data structure algorithalms classes,
它不同于常规的数据结构算法类，
because these things are backed by disk,
因为这些东西是由磁盘支持的，
and we're having multiple threads running at the same time,
我们有多个线程同时运行，
and there's a bunch of things we need to do to hide that, those [],
我们需要做一系列的事情来隐藏这些[]，
SQL Server, a whole other [],
SQL Server ，一个完全不同的[] ，
SQL Server, they have, they actually have their own user space [] routines,
SQL Server ，他们有自己的用户空间例程，
so like if you're traversing the data structure,
所以如果你在遍历数据结构，
and the thing I need, I can't get the latch,
而我需要的，我拿不到 latch ，
instead of just spinning, they go back to their own user space schedule
不只是旋转，而是回到它们自己的用户空间调度器，
and says, I can't, I can't run,
并说，我不能运行，
because I'm waiting for this latch,
因为我在等待这个 latch ，
and then they take your thread away
然后他们拿走你的线程，
and have it do some other work,
让它做一些其他的工作，
and then they may know what latch you're waiting for,
然后他们可能知道你在等待什么 latch ，
they're actually doing some tracking,
它们实际上在做一些跟踪，
who's waiting for what latches inside of it,
谁在等待里面的什么 latch ，
and they can do that,
他们能够做到这个，
because everything is [] routines in user space,
因为用户空间中的一切都是[]例程，
very few, nobody else does,
很少有人，没有人这么做，
that SQL Server does some really cool things.
SQL Server 做了一些非常酷的事情。
All right, cool. Any other questions?
好的，酷。还有其他问题吗？
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, so his question is,
是的，所以他的问题是，
let me go back here,
让我回到这里，
his question is,
他的问题是，
if I'm traversing along with sibling nodes,
如果我遍历兄弟节点，
this one here, right,
这里这个，
if they're trying to get across,
如果它们想要通过，
why does, so T2 is that B,
所以 T2 是 B ，
T1 is that C,
T1 是 C ，
why does T2 need to hold the latch on B in order to get to C,
为什么 T2 需要持有 B 的 latch 为了获取 C ，
because you need to know,
因为你需要知道，
that the sibling pointer is still valid,
兄弟指针仍然有效，
then this is the right, the right node,
那么这就是正确的节点，
that this is the right node you'd be looking to, right,
这就是你要寻找的正确节点，
and you know that if there was an update,
如果有更新，
because you hold this in read mode,
因为你把它保持在读模式，
nobody can update it,
没有人可以更新它，
so you know that no one's gonna replace B with something
所以，没有人会用一些东西替换 B ，
with some, you know, some other new version of it,
使用一些其他新版本的东西，
they now point to something else
它们现在指向其他东西，
and but you're still gonna follow the pointer
但你仍然要沿着指针，
to whatever you thought was there before, right,
指向你以前认为在那里的任何东西，
so you have to hold the latches
所以你必须持有 latch ，
until you know you're safe on the other side,
直到你知道你在另一边是安全的，
then you can go ahead and release it.
然后你就可以继续，并释放它。
Same thing, it's going from top down,
同样，它是自上而下的，
you need to know that,
你需要知道，
like the thing I'm jumping to next is what I should be jumping into.
我接下来要跳到的东西是我应该跳到的。
Yes.
是的。
Yeah, so, so this question, same as,
是的，所以，这个问题，就像，
it is a question that like,
这是一个问题，
last time, I talked about how systems like Postgres have sibling pointers at inner nodes,
上一次，我谈到了像 Postgres 这样的系统如何在内部节点上有兄弟指针，
even though I'm only showing leaf nodes here,
尽管我在这里只显示了叶子节点，
and if I use those inner node sibling pointers to jump, again, horizontally,
如果我使用这些内部节点的兄弟指针来水平地跳转，
how do I take latches on those
我怎么才能获取这些上面的 latch ，
and make sure things are still correct,
并确保一切正常，
so the protocol, everything I'm describing here, would still work,
所以协议，我在这里描述的一切，仍然有效，
if,
如果，
for reads, it simple,
对于读取，它是简单的，
could you just take the read latch across,
你只需获取读 latch 通过，
because anybody else coming above you,
因为任何高于你的人，
once you are write,
一旦你是写入，
they'll see your read latch and they'll stop,
他们就会看到你的读 latch ，他们会停止，
anything below, below that side of the tree that was doing an update,
树下面的任何东西做更新，
you'll get [blocked], you take the take the read down,
你被阻塞，获取读 latch 向下，
so that's fine,
所以这是可以的，
for doing updates,
对于更新，
I think it works the same way as you come across,
我认为它的工作方式，像你[]一样，
if what you're trying to do below is not safe,
如果你在下面尝试做的事情不安全，
then you still hold latches for those things,
然后你仍然持有那些东西的 latch ，
the protocol still works,
协议仍然有效，
even if you have to go across horizontally and go down.
即使你必须水平地通过并向下。
You still have the deadlock,
你仍然会有死锁，
if everyone's trying to go across vertically on you or horizontally on on you too,
如果每个人都试图垂直通过你或水平通过你，
and then you do the same thing I'm describing here.
然后你做我在这里描述的同样的事情。
Is there another question?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay, cool.
好的，酷。
So, all right.
所以，好的。
Just to finish up.
做个总结。
This is hard
这很难，
and I'm showing you like the most simplest version to do,
我向你展示的是最简单的版本，
latch crabbing and that [],
latch 抓取和[]，
we're not going to cover this in this class,
我们不会在这节课中讨论这个，
but there's way more complicated schemes,
但还有更复杂的方案，
you can have [] latches,
你可以有[] latch ，
you can have delayed updates,
你可以延迟更新，
you can do the B tree stuff,
你可以做 Bε 树的事情，
where you delay things,
在那里你延迟事情，
there's a bunch of other stuff you can do this,
你还可以做很多其他的事情，
the B tree is a lock-free B+ tree from Microsoft,
Bε 是来自微软的无锁的 B+ 树，
that's a whole other nightmare.
这是另一个噩梦。
Again, this is hard, but this is good,
再次，这很难，但这很好，
because this is like you take this class
因为这你上这门课，
and this is why,
这就是为什么，
you know, you don't want your, your random Javascript programmer
你不想让你的随机的 Javascript 程序员
building your, your B+ tree, your data structures in your database systems,
在你的数据库系统中构建你的 B+ 树数据结构，
you want CMU students like you guys that know what the hell they're doing
你们希望像你们这样 CMU 学生知道他们在做什么，
and make sure that they don't cause problems.
并确保他们不会造成问题。
And so again we talk about hash table,
所以我们再次讨论哈希表，
we talk about B B+ tree today,
我们今天讨论 B+ 树，
but these techniques of this idea of
但是这种想法的技巧，
like everything's going the same direction
比如一切都朝着同一个方向走，
or I kill myself as soon as I can't get something and restart
或者我一旦拿不到东西就杀死自己并重新启动，
like this is, this is relevant to, to a bunch of other data structures in systems as well.
这也与系统中的很多其他数据结构相关。
I feel like we should just call this course, kill yourself,
我觉得我们应该把这门课叫作杀死你自己，
I actually asking for CMU to get involved,
我让 CMU 涉及其中，
I don't need that trouble, sorry,
我不想有这个麻烦，抱歉，
one year, somebody did complain,
有一年，有人抱怨，
that did say kill yourself a lot, sorry.
说了很多杀死你自己，抱歉。
All right, so,
好的，所以，
so next class we're talking about sorting or sort aggregations,
所以，下一节课我们将讨论排序或排序聚合，
so this point we're moving up the stack,
在这一点上，我们要向上移动，
now we can actually start executing queries,
现在我们可以开始执行查询了，
fantastic, right,
太棒了，对吧，
so I won't be here on Monday or I'm not teaching,
所以我星期一不会在这里讲课，
Jignesh Patel be the other professor,
Jignesh Patel 是另一位教授，
he's going to start teaching on Monday
他将于星期一开始讲课，
and then wednesday, next week,
然后是下星期三，
he and I are both gone,
他和我都走了，
I'm going to the Postgres conference in New York,
我要去纽约参加 Postgres 会议，
I'm giving a keynote there about databases,
我将在那里做一个关于数据库主题演讲，
might have to talk to [],
可能必须和[]讨论，
but like we'll have one of my PhD students,
但是我们有一个我的博士生，
my number one PhD student Matt Butrovich
我的头号博士生 Matt butucevic ，
will be teaching on Wednesday next week about Joins, okay?
将在下周三教授有关 Join 方面的课程。
And then Jignesh is awesome,
然后 Jignesh 是很棒的，
Jignesh, asked him about growing up in India,
Jignesh ，问他关于在印度长大的事情，
because before he joined CMU,
因为在他加入 CMU 之前，
he was telling me crazy stories,
他讲了一些疯狂的故事，
he used to get in fights every morning on the bus going to school,
他过去每天早上在上学的公交车上打架，
I think he carried knife, ask him about it.
我想他带着小刀，问他这件事。
Okay, and then we'll, we'll talk about the midterm on, on next week as well, okay.
好的，我们也将在下周谈论期中考试。